<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An abridgement of Christian perfection Conteining many excellent precepts, &amp; aduertisments, touching the holy, and sacred mysticall diuinity. Written in Italian, by Fa. Achilles Galliardi of the Society of Iesus, &amp;translated into English, A.H. of the same society</title>
            <title>Breve compendio intorno alla perfezione cristiana. English</title>
            <author>Galliardi, Achilles, 1537-1607.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1625</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 163 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 100 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01420</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11539</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120493</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855689</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855689</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21191</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01420)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21191)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1024:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An abridgement of Christian perfection Conteining many excellent precepts, &amp; aduertisments, touching the holy, and sacred mysticall diuinity. Written in Italian, by Fa. Achilles Galliardi of the Society of Iesus, &amp;translated into English, A.H. of the same society</title>
                  <title>Breve compendio intorno alla perfezione cristiana. English</title>
                  <author>Galliardi, Achilles, 1537-1607.</author>
                  <author>Percy, Mary, Lady, 1570-1642.</author>
                  <author>Hoskins, Anthony, 1568-1615, attributed name.</author>
                  <author>Berinzaga, Isabella Cristina, 1551?-1624, attributed name. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The second edition.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>216 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>English College Press],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Saint-Omer :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno M. DC. XXV. [1625]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Breve compendio intorno alla perfezione cristiana.</note>
                  <note>Actually written by Christina Bellinzaga with the collaboration of Gagliardi, who was her spiritual adviser--STC.</note>
                  <note>A.H. = Anthony Hoskins.</note>
                  <note>In the 1626 issue, the translator is given on title page as "the La. M.P."; the translation was probably a collaboration between Lady Mary Percy and Anthony Hoskins.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication and printer from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Society of Jesus Library, Mount Street.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Perfection --  Religious aspects --  Catholic Church --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Asceticism --  Catholic Church --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21191:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21191:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ABRIDGMENT OF CHRISTIAN PERFECTION. CONTEINING Many excellent
Precepts, &amp; Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertiſments, touching the holy, and ſacred my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall
Diuinity.</p>
            <p>Written in Italian, by <hi>Fa. Achilles Galliardi</hi> of the
Society of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> &amp; tranſlated
into English:</p>
            <p>By A. H. of the ſame Society.</p>
            <p>THE SECOND EDITION.</p>
            <p>Imprinted Anno M.DC.XXV.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:21191:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21191:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE RELIGIOVS MEN AND WOMEN OF OVR NATION. AND To all others
who deſire to attayne to the eminent ſtate of Christia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Perfection: health
in our Lord.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HIS Little Booke (Deuout Religious in Chriſt Ieſus) being
firſt written in Italian by the <pb n="4" facs="tcp:21191:3"/>
               <hi>R. Father Achilles
Galliardi,</hi> of the Society of IESVS, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered ouer, in written papers
only, vnto an Honourable and very deuout Lady of <hi>Millan,</hi> for her
priuate inſtruction, and better aduancement in ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all matters, was
ſome yeares paſt gotten out of her Cloſet, and communicated to more, then
it was at firſt intended. For a little after it was carryed into France and
there tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and printed in the French tongue; but with ſo many
o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions, obſcurities, and other faults, contrary to the Authors
meaning, that in many places it could hardly be drawne to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny perfect
ſenſe: the which <pb n="5" facs="tcp:21191:3"/>ſome perſons of great zeale, &amp;
well experienced Maiſters of Spirit perceauing, and lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting that ſo
excellent a Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure ſhold be obſcured &amp; clow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in ſuch darknes;
did care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully labour to correct what was amiſſe, by making cleere the
obſcure places and by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoring of many paſſages to their proper
ſenſe, which were before corrupt and intricate: that ſo being publiſhed
anew, it might appeare worthy to be preſented to the view of
poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</p>
            <p>In this little Worke then, is conteyned, and ſet before our
eyes, Doctrine of ſo great Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, endeauouring ſo to 
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:21191:4"/>purify the intention, &amp; reduce the mind of man to
conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and vnion with the Will of God, that the view of ſo great a
light, may perhaps dazle the eyes of ſuch, as yet do looke throgh the clowd
of ſelfe-loue, and are not fully reſolued to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell their inward enemyes;
&amp; in that reſpect it is not inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, or directed to any ſuch. And
much leſſe is it offered to ſenſuall minds, who cannot iudge, or
diſcerne the worth of ſuch a pearle, but would ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple it vnder
their feete, then tread the pathe which leades to ſuch a treaſure.</p>
            <p>But I doubt not to de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me it fitly preſented to the reading <pb n="7" facs="tcp:21191:4"/>of all
ſuch, as haue entred, or reſolued to enter the pathes of Perfection, by
imitation of Chriſt our Lord, in practiſe &amp; performance of the
Counſells Eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gelicall. For of ſuch minds we may with reaſon hope, that
firſt God for his part, as he hath called them from the purſuite of worldly
vanities to the veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of his diuine loue: ſo he will be no leſſe
bountiful vnto them in aſſiſting their endeauours with plenty of grace,
vntill he haue perfected the work which himſelfe hath begun in their
ſoules.</p>
            <p>And of their part, as they haue receaued from God ſo much light,
as to find this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, <pb n="8" facs="tcp:21191:5"/>and ſo much wiſdome as to
know the value therof, and ſo much fortitude of mind as to contemne their
former worldly eſtate, for the purchaſe of this field or ſtate of
Religious life: ſo we may iuſtly expect at their handes, that according to
the light, wiſedome, and fortitude which they haue receaued, they ſhould be
deſirous, and glad to labour in digging out the ſayd treaſure, and
getting it entierly into their owne poſſeſſion: and therefore alſo
that they ought neyther to be loath to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take the labour of digging, nor
yet to thinke much, if hauing gotten the gold, to ſeuer it from the earth and
droſſe which ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hereth <pb n="9" facs="tcp:21191:5"/>vnto it. And this true in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention
of benefitting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues (which is neuer wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting in any wiſe man that
hath fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d but an earthly Treaſure) is as much as this Book requireth, in the
practiſe of whatſoeuer is heere preſcribed.</p>
            <p>For firſt we be heere aduiſed to dig &amp; deſcend into our
own nothing by <hi>Anihilation:</hi> then to caſt vp and throw from vs all
the earthly ſubſtance which lyeth betweene vs &amp; the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and
this by <hi>Diſappropria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> or as it is called in the Ghoſpell, by
<hi>Renunciation</hi> of all thinges which we poſſeſſe. Then we be led
by the vertue of <hi>Indifferency</hi> to cleanſe it alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing 
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:21191:6"/>found, from the duſt of our priuate affections, and
ſelf-in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt. And thus the gold being gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into our poſſeſſion
it the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> teacheth vs firſt how to puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy the ſame from the droſſe of
all ſelf-loue, by the <hi>Conformity</hi> of our will to the Will of God.
Secondly, to refine it yet more from the baſer kind of mettall, which is
ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> much mixed with this diuine gold, and yet hardly by the eye to be
diſcerned, but the touchſtone of Chriſt his example doth try it, &amp;
the fire of Charity doth refine it, ſo that it then comes to be <hi>Aurum
igni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi> ſpoken of in the Apoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyps, and one thing, as it were, with
the fire it ſelfe; and this <pb n="11" facs="tcp:21191:6"/>is therefore called
<hi>Vniformity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then remayneth only, that this gold thus feruent and plia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to
the will of him that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth it, receaue the ſtampe of the heauenly King,
that ſo it may be currant coyne in his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine Court: in which it is only a
Patient, and nothing is expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted of it, but that it take, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
reſiſtance, what impreſſion the workman is beſt pleaſed to
impoſe. This is the worke of Grace in the ſoule; the worke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man is God
himſelfe, and the ſtampe he imprinteth in it, is his owne Image: and ſo
this ſixt and higheſt degree of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection is called
<hi>Deiformity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this ſtate the Soule hauing <pb n="12" facs="tcp:21191:7"/>firſt
reiected al impediments to her well-doing, rooted out all euill habits, planted
in her ſelfe the habits of ſolid vertues, and ſeuered from her intention
all ſelfe-loue; yea hauing by the help of Gods Grace, purified euen her
moſt inward deſires, &amp; all ſenſible inclinations, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the
infection of ſelfe-intereſt, then is her will not conformed only, but
vnited vnto the will of God, and ſo transformed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſame, that now it
ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth not to be her will that worketh, but the will of God which worketh
in her: as though ſhe had giuen her own hart vnto Chriſt, and (as we read
of <hi>Catherine</hi> of <hi>Stena</hi>) had <pb n="13" facs="tcp:21191:7"/>receaued his in
exchange, to be in her, from that tyme for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, the beginning and firſt
motiue of all her operations.</p>
            <p>Of which eſtate alſo we may vnderſtand the wordes of the
Apoſtle <hi>Gal</hi> 2. when he ſayd, <hi>V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> autem, iam nonego,
viu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t verò in me
Christus:</hi> And I liue now not I, but Chriſt liueth in me. Much like as we
ſee the graffe which is inſerted into another ſtock, which liueth indeed
in it ſelfe, &amp; bringeth forth fruit, but not by the life it had before,
from it owne naturall roote; but by the ſap &amp; life it now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaueth from
the new ſtock in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which it is graffed, in which it growes, &amp; by which
it liues.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <p> 
               <gap reason="missing" resp="#OXF" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:21191:8"/>many aduiſes in the booke, (eſpecially in the Chapters
of the ſecond &amp; third Eſtate) w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ere i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ught that the ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le must be content
to f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rgo firſt all actiue
operat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on, and practiſe euen of
vertues themſelues, and lastly to be depriued euen of the paſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tue alſo ſo farr as it may ſeeme
ſenſible vnto the ſoule that it is her own work. And this to the end that
Gods will may be the pure, and only mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue of her will and workes
whatſoeuer; thou must beware in theſe, &amp; the like ſentences, of two
ſeuerall doctrines or errors, wholy contrary to that which is beere intended.
The one, leaſt thou thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke that a ſoule being come to that eſtate, doth
not indeed work with her owne will, but that God then worketh all in her, ſo
that thoſe workes be not really the act<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ons of the ſoule, but of God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe; which thing is both
falſe and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd The other error is, that a ſoule in this ſtate of
Perfection should not doe any thing, but as ſeeing her ſelf to be 
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:21191:8"/>cleerly moued therunto by the will of God, and in a manner
compelled by the ſame to doe all her actions, ſo that she in the meane tyme
should be idle, vntill the feele this impulſion from God. This doctrine would
nourish ſlouth in the ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le, yea and breed, if not bring forth, he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſy
alſo againſt the freedome of our wil, and againſt the neceſsitie of our
concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence with the grace of God: all which are not different only, but
contrary to the intentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Author, as (beſides the authority of the
<hi>Pariſian</hi> Doctours who approued this booke, when it was tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated
out of Italian, and ſet forth in their owne language) the diligent &amp;
impartiall Reader may alſo by himſelf eaſily diſcerne, if he mark wel
the whole diſcourſe. For he shall find it here requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that one omit no
practiſe, or proofe of likely meanes, either in rooting out of euill, or in
planting of good habits. Alſo that all the rules, &amp; aduiſes of this
boo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke, are to be applied to euery mans eſtate <pb n="18" facs="tcp:21191:9"/>and that he
omitting no part of his du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, doe practiſe the ſame, togeather with the
actions which his estate and institu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te require. Lastly that this
<hi>Subtractio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> of actiue and paſs<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ue Will, touching the acts of vertue, is the worke only of God in
the ſoule, with which (when the ſoule doth perceaue it to be ſo) it must
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre as with the will of God, to will the ſame thing, as our dutie doth
bind vs. And this is no other thing then we find in daily practiſe, though
all doe not feele it a like, nor all follow this rule, as they should, when
they feele it. Ye happeneth vnto vs more or leſse whenſoeuer any
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation by Gods appointment doth fall vpon vs, for in that caſe we
finde our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues leſſe apt then before to will, or worke any good, yea,
or to ſuffer the proceeding of that good (which before we deſired) with any
contentment: and this deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion may ſo increaſe, that it shall ſeeme
to vs, our deſire carrieth vs wholy to the contrary of that we had
reſolued. But all <pb n="19" facs="tcp:21191:9"/>this is only in the inferiour part of
ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſoule to wit in our naturall
inclination, which for the time is left to it ſelf, by <hi>Subtraction</hi>
of that effect, and fruit of grace by which it was before comforted,
ſtrengthened, and enabled to performe good actions, and concurre to
ſupernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall vertues, with deſire and delight: which to be the effectes
and fruits of gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, the Apoſtle teacheth, <hi>Galat. 5.22.</hi> when he
ſaith: <hi>Fructus autem ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus eſt charitas, gaudium, pax, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tientia
&amp;c.</hi> So that all this while gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce is not diminished in the ſuperiour
part of the ſoule, nor the vertues leſſe perfect which are placed therin,
but only there-doundance, fruit, and effect of that grace is ſtopped, and
ſubtracted for the time, from the inferiour part, to increaſe the batta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le which the ſoule is to bane, and
the victory which it is to obtaine, by conſtantly conforming, and vniting her
will to Gods, notwithſtanding that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed difficultie; yea by
renouncing <pb n="20" facs="tcp:21191:10"/>her owne naturall will and inclination,
transforming the ſame into the will of God, and ſo ſaying with our
Sauiour Christ in the like caſe: <hi>Non mea, ſed tua voluntas
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, Pater:</hi> not my will, o Father, but thine be done. In whoſe
example we may ſee, that the practiſe of this point may stand with all
Perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, which could not be wanting in his actions. So that the ſcope of
this doctrine is not to make vs idle or remiſſe in wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, nor to expect
that God should doe all in vs, and that our will should haue no part in the
action: but it requireth, that we doe coopera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e with Gods grace, and labour with all diligence, whileſt we can.
And when by Gods ordinance we feele that our ſenſible forces do faile vs,
and that we are not now able to creep, who before were able to runne in the
wayes of God (as the Prophet ſaith, <hi>Pſal. 118.32.</hi>) <hi>cùm
dilatater cor noſtrum,</hi> whileſt he dilated our hart with ioy and
comfort; we muſt then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme <pb n="21" facs="tcp:21191:10"/>our will to God, yea, and
be glad to transforme our weake will into his ſtrength of goodnes, to vnite
our drop of water to his ſea of graces, and to ſay with our actiue will
(though our incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations striue againſt it) that his will shall be ours, and
therfore that we deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re his will may be done with vs in all thinges,
howſoeuer our in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>our part doe, according to nature,
deſire the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary.</p>
            <p>This is the Perfection vnto which this Booke leadeth: the
practiſe wherof we may ſee both vſed, and declared by God to his beloued
Apostle, as may be gathered out of the first Chapter of the <hi>2. Epiſt. ad
Cor.</hi> and it is the highest which the ſoule can arriue vnto in this life.
For as the will of God is infinitly good, and euen goodnes it ſelf, ſo the
nearer we come vnto it, the more we ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach to a good and perfect estate.
Ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can there be, euen by imagination conceaued, a higher Perfection, or
grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <pb n="22" facs="tcp:21191:11"/>happines, either in this world or the next, then
to be vnited vnto God, the fountaine of all goodnes. In this life it is to be
done by grace, and in the next by glorie. This
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>le Booke, gen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le Reader, will lead thee to the one,
and thy dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent practiſe of what it teacheth, will bring thee to the
other.</p>
            <p>Christ IESVS gra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt vs
grace to ſeeke this treaſure with true deſire, &amp; finding it, to vſe
it to our best commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. We shall doe it the better, if we pray hartily for
one another, which I purpoſe to doe for all, that will endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to
practiſe this Booke, &amp; do craue the like of them for my greater needs.
Farewell.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>A. H.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <head>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:21191:11"/>AN ABRIDGMENT OF CHRISTIAN PERFECTION.</head>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <head>WHAT PERFECTION ought to be preſuppoſed in the Soule that
entreth into the practiſe of that, which is treated off in this
diſcourſe. CHAP. I.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HIS Perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth a firme and reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute deſire in the
ſoule that vndertaketh it, &amp; a determinate and ſet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed purpoſe <pb n="24" facs="tcp:21191:12"/>to attayne vnto it, and
aboue all, it muſt be as the marke at which ſhe aymeth, and the end which
ſhe pretendeth in all her actions. It requireth alſo, that ſhe giue her
ſelfe to mortification of her ſenſes and paſſions, endeauouring to
ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due the repugnance and contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction which riſeth of them, and to
obtaine full dominion and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory ouer them. Moreouer that ſhe apply her
ſelfe wholy to the mortification, and abnegation of her will, and proper
iudgement; vnder an entire obedience and a ful direction of her Superiors, euen
with all the forces of her ſoule. That likewiſe ſhe ſo apply her ſelf
to vertue according to the occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s occurring, or in any other ſort; &amp;
principally to charity, to the loue of God and her neighbour, that ſhe be not
in this way alwayes rude, and as a beginner, but well ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uanced 
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:21191:12"/>and profited by progreſſe of time; at the leaſt ſhe
muſt haue attayned a firme reſolution, to be willing rather to dye, then to
of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend God, yea although but veni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, or to commit one of the leaſt
defects againſt perfection, in ſuch ſort, that the ſinne ſhe doth
com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, be by meere occurring frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. The cauſe, wherefore all this that
hath byn ſayd ought to be preſuppoſed, is, for that a firme purpoſe of
al theſe things in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, is moſt neceſſary for the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayning of
Perfection. And it is certaine that whoſoeuer without a very earneſt
deſire of theſe things doth with coldnes, and negligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce ſeeke after
vertue, giuing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to his proper commodities, &amp; ſelfe
intereſts, liuing like a liberti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, and with a will to remayne in his old
habits, without amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; can neuer attayne, nor come <pb n="26" facs="tcp:21191:13"/>neere to Perfection, &amp; much leſſe to this that is the
higheſt of all.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <head>TWO PRINCIPSES in which conſiſteth Perfection. CHAP.
II.</head>
            <p>ALL the building of ſo high Perfection is fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded in theſe two
Principles, which conſiſt in practice: and therefore by the vſe of them,
being attentiue to the dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly actions of his vocation, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution,
aſſuredly he ſhall come to the toppe, and full height of all his
building. The firſt principle is, to haue a meane, &amp; baſe eſteeme of
things created, and aboue all of himſelfe: fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which eſteeme ought to be
deriued at leaſt in affection, an entire forſaking of al creatures, and
arenouncing of himſelfe. And concerning his affection, to haue 
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:21191:13"/>alwayes this firme in his will &amp; reſolution, but to
put it in practiſe principally when it is needfull. And from this ought to be
deriued alſo a true knowledg of the with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing that God worketh in vs,
admitting, and accepting it with a ready will, to wit, to content our ſelues,
and with great ioy of hart to accept it, when our Lord retyreth himſelfe a
little from vs, or depriueth vs of anything what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Principle is, to haue a moſt high eſteeme of God,
not by the way of penetration with Theologicall conceipts, or the like high
pointes of Diuinity, for this few can reach vnto, and it is not neceſſary;
but rather by the meane of a great promptitude, &amp; entire ſubmiſſion
of the will, and of the whole man, to the maieſty of God, to adore him, and
to doe <pb n="28" facs="tcp:21191:14"/>whatſoeuer he exacteth of vs, for his greater
glory, without any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of ours, how holy ſoeuer it be. For which
eſteeme it ſufficeth, that the ſoule with the light of fayth apprehend
God (as we are taught in our Creed) as Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, the ſoueraigne good, our
end: and that for the great loue he bare vnto vs, he was mooued to make
himſelfe man, to ſuffer paines and death for our ſakes. Moreouer that he
is alwaies preſent with vs, and in all things gouerneth vs, as well in
thoſe of nature, as of grace: and in particuler calleth vs with a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular
vocation, to labour for ſo high Perfection, &amp; the like; which ſpeciall
fauours our Lord giueth to euery one conformable to his capacity, &amp;
according to the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of grace.</p>
            <p>Of this ſo excellent, and high eſteem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ought to ſpring a full and <pb n="29" facs="tcp:21191:14"/>entire
conformity with the diuine Will, which alwayes muſt be the rule of all our
deſignemens, affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions and dayly operations. This ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner of working by the
foreſaid meane, with the vſe of theſe two Principles, bringeth the Soule
to the vnion, and transformation in God, which is called Deification, not by
the myſticall way of raui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing out of our ſenſes, and eleua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of
the vnderſtanding, nor by moſt vehement affections, that are deriued, and
proceed from thence; for this is ſubiect to a thouſand il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſions, and to
great labour, with danger of infirmity of body, and ruine of ſpirit, and
ſuch payne for the moſt part auaileth little, and few do attayne vnto it:
But it is by the beaten and common way, to wit, by the will wholy confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med,
&amp; with great ſtability tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed into the diuine Will, by 
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:21191:15"/>perfect loue, the which maketh it to worke all in God, and
for God euen without light and of this all are capable, and any that wil, may
come vnto it with ioy, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, but yet not without payne and labour. And
after this there followeth ordinarily many other giftes of light, and diuine
affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but they are to be taken as graces that are giuen <hi>gratis</hi>
as truly they are, and we ought not to be too carefull for them, or to rely
much vpon them. They are diuers according to the variety of ſoules, to ſome
more, to others leſſe; and there is no rule on our part, but all dependeth
of God, and ought to be wholy ſubmitted to his diuine pleaſure.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:21191:15"/>
            <head>OF THE FIRST Estate: &amp; firſt of Anihilation. CHAP.
III.</head>
            <p>THE foreſayd principles ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to the diuerſities of our
occaſions, actions, and motions, do make the ſoule to walke with continuall
progreſſe, from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, euen vnto the end of Perfection, and all is
reduced into three eſtates, euery one of which, and principally the firſt,
contay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth diuers degrees, that maketh the ſoule mount, as it were, by
cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne degrees, going from one e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate vnto another, euen to the laſt.
In the firſt eſtate, the ſoule walketh by the way of the knowledge, &amp;
baſe eſteeme of her ſelfe, which is done in diuers manners, and
prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally in foure.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:21191:16"/>1. The firſt is in acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, and
eſteeming herſelfe pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly nothing, ſeing that of nothing ſhe was
created, and ſhould be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted into nothing of her ſelfe, if God did not
conſerue her. Vnto which it helpeth much, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare herſelfe to the whole
world, to all men, to heauen, to Saints, &amp; to God himſelfe, in reſpect
of which things, ſhe knoweth her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to be not ſo much as a little drop
of water, compared with the ſea</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly in houlding her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe for the moſt vile, and
vnpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable creature of all, how vile ſoeuer they be, as is duſt, a
ſinke, an Apoſteme &amp;c. all theſe things being good for ſome vſe,
but ſhe for nothing, but to offend God.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thirdly in thinking herſelfe the greateſt ſinner in
the world, yea greater then all the diuels put <pb n="33" facs="tcp:21191:16"/>togeather,
and worthy of more chaſtiſement, attributing to her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe al the ſinnes
that are commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and that all their tormentes duly might be inflicted vpon
her. For there is no ſin but ſhe might haue committed it, if God had not
preſerued her. Exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples of this may be ſeene in the liues of <hi>S.
Francis,</hi> and <hi>S. Catherine</hi> of <hi>Siena.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. The fourth conſiſteth in this, that ſhe ought to
deſcend to the knowledge of the thinges of the world, the better to contemne
them: and for the reiecting of them, ſhe muſt make choice of the vileſt
and baſeſt of them, as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning her place, garments, and any thing els;
yet ſo notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, that ſhe affect not ſingulari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: and ſhe
muſt eſteeme the moſt abiect corner in the houſe the fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt habitation for her, and that
the office, or charge ſhe hath, exce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth <pb n="34" facs="tcp:21191:17"/>much her merits; and that ſhe is not
worthy of them, much leſſe of greater. The foreſayd practice bringeth a
man to a true anihilatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of himſelfe. And although he doth not apprehend
ſuch conceipts in his vnderſtanding, as may clearely repreſent ſuch
baſenes vnto him, as he would; yet doth not he leaue to haue that eſteeme
of himſelfe, ſeeing that he, who willingly abaſeth himſelfe, and
preferreth all creatures, how vile ſoeuer they be, before him, eſteemeth
and repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth himſelfe alwayes the leaſt: &amp; he that knoweth not the
practiſe of this anihilation, knoweth not the profit, and commodity
there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
            <p>Thirdly in the ſoule that is fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded thus in her owne nothing,
there followeth alſo the diſappro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priation or true abnegation, the
ſubtraction or withdrawing that <pb n="35" facs="tcp:21191:17"/>God accuſtometh to
worke in the ſoule, and the conformity with the diuine will, which maketh a
man to be transformed into God: &amp; theſe things as they haue diuers
obiects, ſo they haue diuers de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, according to the order that
followeth.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <head>OF THE FIRT degree of Abnegation, Subtraction, Conformity: and of
the Abiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Anihilation of our ſelues. CHAP. IIII.</head>
            <p>FIRST, and principally there is wrought in the ſoule a full, &amp;
entire renunciation of al things created, that are indifferent, as life, death,
health, all commodities, taſt and intereſt of them, offices, dignities,
poſſeſſions, and other <pb n="36" facs="tcp:21191:18"/>the like things; and this is
to be done, firſt with the affections, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing them entie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly, and all deſire or will ſhe may
haue of the: and for her owne part, ſhe ought to caſt all deſire, and
affection, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tion that
ſhe may haue therin, and the hopes of any commodity, taſt and pleaſure
that may be had therby, euen as if ſhe were dead.</p>
            <p>Secondly by worke, leauing actually that which is ſuperfluou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and retayning only that which is
needfull to her, according to her ſtate, with the counſayle, &amp;
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of her Superiors. To this doth correſpond the ſubtraction, or
withdrawing, that God doth in vs of the like things, to wit, of life, by
ſending vs death, of health, by viſiting vs with ſicknes, of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities
and meanes when they are taken from vs, of pleaſures and ſolaces, ſending
vs paynes: and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally <pb n="37" facs="tcp:21191:18"/>of any other worldly cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge,
whereof we haue experience al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt euery hou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e. All being done by the d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ume prouidence in ſuch ſort, that there paſſeth not any
day, in which our Lord doth not take from vs, and depriue vs (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the
variety of his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence) of many obiects, &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities, concerning
theſe tranſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, and fading things. And he that is free from all
affection to the like thinges, admitteth with great alacrity all priuation of
them, and eaſily contemneth them all, how great ſoeuer they be.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe to this ſubtraction, &amp; priuation correſpondeth a
mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaylous conformity with the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine Will, not deſiring any created thing
whatſoeuer, but that which our Lord willeth, and that which he giueth vs,
reioycing to be, by the meanes of theſe changes &amp; va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieties.
<gap reason="missing" resp="#OXF" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:21191:19"/>reſaid
conformity, a very great, &amp; true loue of God, ſeeing there is taken away
al the hinderances of any created thing, that was bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weene God &amp; the
Soule. And by this meanes the ſoule commeth to vnite herſelfe perfectly
with her Creatour, &amp; to tranforme her ſelf perfectly into him: from which
ordinarily followeth great gifts, as lights, affections, and diuine motions:
but for theſe we are not to be much carefull, but to ſeeke aboue all, to
ſeparate our ſelues with all our power from created things, and wholy to
reſigne our ſelues vnto God. And this is the extaſy, and rauiſhing of
the will, and not of the Vnderſtanding, which is much greater, and high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,
and which Deifieth the ſoule more.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:21191:19"/>
            <head>THE SECOND Degree. Chap. V.</head>
            <p>VVE ought to paſſe fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in ſubtraction, or withdrawing our
ſelues from things created. For not only this ſubtraction ought to be of
indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent thinges, as is ſaid, but alſo of holy and ſpirituall, that
are mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to vnite the ſpirit with God; yet not, as of ſuch, muſt we
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priue our ſelues of them, but for ſo much as vnder the colour of
holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, there may be hid proper loue, and particuler intereſt; &amp; of
theſe there is to be noted many degres. The firſt, and that which is
com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly vnderſtood of ſpirituall men to be the loweſt, or baſeſt,
is <pb n="42" facs="tcp:21191:20"/>touching ſpirituall conſolations, redounding euen to
the affections of the hart, that are ſenſitiue, to wit, tendernes, feruour,
teares, ſweetnes in our operations, &amp; great facility ſurmounting
diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties, by aboundance of ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall delight: of which things we ought
to depriue our ſelues, and not to ceaſe vntil ſuch time, as we haue no
more feeling of any deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re to them.</p>
            <p>The depriuing our ſelues of theſe, conſiſteth in not making
any eſteeme, or any accompt of them, conſidering that theſe faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities,
that induce vs to worke, proceed not of any habit, or par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticuler gifts or
graces, nor princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally of charity; but only of this ſweetnes and pleaſure
taken ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, which is an obiect very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionate to ſelfeloue, and
parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culer intereſt, which nouriſheth <pb n="43" facs="tcp:21191:20"/>it ſelfe with
ſelfe contentment, &amp; pleaſure, and commeth in tyme vnto a ſpirituall
gluttony: and to receaue ſatisfaction in this, or to make any great eſteeme
therof, is no other thing, then to conuert holy obiects into our delights &amp;
pleaſures, and abuſe holy things, accommodating them to our guſt, and
feeling. A very great vice, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it be ſecret and hid, from which
eaſily may ſpring diuers vaine delightes, proud illuſions, and
diabolicall deceipts, and a thouſand other euills. Alſo we muſt not
thinke that vertue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendeth of them or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſteth the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rin, but we muſt
know, that this is a childiſh thing, and that with this ſweetnes &amp;
facility, a litle ſtrength and vertue is ſufficient to make vs imbrace the
hardeſt, and moſt difficult matters: therfore we muſt depriue our
ſelues of al deſire <pb n="44" facs="tcp:21191:21"/>of them as of a meane thing, &amp;
of little eſteme: and by the foreſaid anihilation, acknowledge our
ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues moſt vnworthy of them, with a totall indifferency to haue them or
not, being incited by vertue &amp; perfection, to vſe them when we haue them,
only for the end that God ſendeth them, to wit; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging them with
great ſubmiſſion, and referring them vnto God, from whome they proceed,
directing in them our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention to eſtabliſh vs, and to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe ſo
much the more in true &amp; ſolide vertues: taking alwaies heed leaſt being
tranſported, and made drunk with this ſwetnes &amp; ſpirituall taſt, we
do not make purpoſes, or dangerous promiſes of vertues, or workes that
ſurpaſſe our forces, and which, when that ſenſible delight and
pleaſure cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, wil ſeeme moſt difficult, yea <pb n="45" facs="tcp:21191:21"/>impoſſible vnto vs.</p>
            <p>And to auoid ſuch danger, the ſubmiſſion already ſpoken
of, hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth greatly; that is, when we admit with great promptitude of hart,
the taking away of ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolations as God is accuſtomed at times to
take from vs, and then to make greater eſtimation of God, and of vertue, then
of any ſuch conſolations, yet labouring ſtill according to thoſe former
motio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, with a greater, and more ardent deſire then euer, without hauing
regard to the contentment of ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loue, but only to the loue of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue it
ſelfe, and for the diuine glory.</p>
            <p>The Conformity with God heere is cleare, and is of great
im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance; for that to vnite him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe with the diuine will, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eth himſelfe, on his part, of ſuch
conſolatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, contenting him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe <pb n="46" facs="tcp:21191:22"/>with his ſpirituall
croſſe whatſoeuer it be; and ſo much the more, for that ſuch taſts,
and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſurpaſſe all things created, and all the pleaſures that
they can affoard: and how much the more a man depriueth himſelfe in this
ſort; ſo much the more he tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formeth himſelfe into God, and perfect
loue, and Deification in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth in him.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <head>THE THIRD Degree. CHAP. VI.</head>
            <p>AFTER the foreſaid degree, there is accuſtomed to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed
&amp; deſcend into the ſoule ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtiall lights, deſires, and
affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of ſtable and ſolid vertues, that are without compariſon much
more high, then the ſweetnes already <pb n="47" facs="tcp:21191:22"/>ſpoken of; for
that they are moſt effectuall meanes for getting of the ſaid ſolid and
ſtable vertues, &amp; haue their being in the ſuperiour part of man. And
then the ſoule ought to mount to the higheſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of forſaking and
renouncing his owne will, &amp; of ſubtraction, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>formity to the diuine
will, with the help of the anihilation, &amp; humble eſteeme aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>Therfore it is neceſſary to be aduertiſed, that although
ſuch lights, &amp; affections be from God in the beginning, and that
preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tly vpon the receiuing, &amp; imbra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of them, they produce in the
ſoule excellent effects, mouing &amp; inciting it to vnite her ſelf with
God, by the meanes of firme &amp; ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid vertues: neuertheles ſoone after
if a man be not well aduiſed, but ſuffer himſelfe to proceed accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
to his naturall inclinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he <pb n="48" facs="tcp:21191:23"/>ordinarily will imbrace
willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuch lights, &amp; affections, with a certaine ſatisfaction, and
a very great contentement in himſelf: which is a hidden delight of
him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in them: and to cooperate with ſuch lights he ſetteth
himſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe to diſcourſe at large, and to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie the naturall forces of
his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, wil, and affections, with the which it ſeemeth vnto
him, that his firſt lights much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, &amp; are interiou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly dilated: which yet is not ſo,
neither is it any effect of God, but only a pure reflection of the ſoule, and
a great contenteme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and pleaſure, which ſhe tak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th of their firſt beginning.</p>
            <p>And thus by little and little, the infuſion of ſuch lights
com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to ceaſe, the naturall, and reaſonable ſtrength of the ſoule
remaineth alone, which ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily is ſelf-loue, which by this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light 
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:21191:23"/>goeth dilating this little that he hath of diuine light,
eſteeming that to be very great which is not: and in this ſort he falleth
into blindnes of pride, &amp; vaine per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion of great vertue, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce do ſpring a thouſand falſhoods, deceipts &amp; illuſions; our
Lord withdrawing his hand, becauſe of the barre of ſelf-loue which man hath
put in his way: and yet ſuch do thinke that they haue great grace infuſed,
&amp; great light, and it is nothing (the beginning only excepted) but only
diſcourſe, and naturall ſtrength. And in the end, abandoned of the diuine
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence, they fall into great faults, &amp; errours; and from hence
often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times proceed very great illuſions which notwithſtanding had
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> good beginning.</p>
            <p>Preſently therfore when the ſoule receaueth ſuch motions,
ſhe <pb n="50" facs="tcp:21191:24"/>ought to humble, and anihilate her ſelfe with great
ſubmiſſion, euen as nothing. And this act roo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth out, and cutteth off
all the force of this delight already ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of. Afterwards ſhe muſt
pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt, that ſhe will not ſeeke any ſelfe-contentment, reputing her
ſelfe moſt vnworthy, as a moſt vile &amp; abiect perso<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; &amp; this to
f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e her ſoule of al
ſelfe-loue, which by reaſon of ſuch lights may enter into it. And heere
ſhe depriueth herſelfe of a much more noble thing then before, &amp; by
this grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vertue is obtained: &amp; although it ſeeme vnto her that ſhe
dimini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth, or decreaſeth, yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding it is not ſo, but the
hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derance is taken away that kept the ſoule backe, &amp; did hurt her
greatly. And our Lord finding the ſoule by ſuch abnegation diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed,
increaſeth with his particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler <pb n="51" facs="tcp:21191:24"/>concourſe, the like
lights and motions, by true &amp; ſolid meanes, although it be not with ſo
great taſt, &amp; pleaſure, and guideth her with great ſafety in the way
of Perfection.</p>
            <p>The ſoule thus depriued by the meanes of ſuch pure &amp; diuine
lights, commeth to refer and attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute them vnto God, feeling her ſelf in
them affected only to the diuine glory, and not vnto any other thing, with
great acknow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledgement of the diuine bounty, who vouchſafeth by diuine
infu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, to abaſe himſelf to ſo vile a thing. And this rule of
ſpirituall motions is a matter of great im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance: for that, if they be not
of God, preſently they wil be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered by this abnegation; and if ſuch
lights come from God, we ſhal be ſecured, that neither ſelfe loue, nor
the diuell can haue any <pb n="52" facs="tcp:21191:25"/>part in them. And moreouer
refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring them vnto God, who hath giuen them vnto vs, we come to make more
eſteeme of the giuer, then of the gifts, and by this mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes get true and
ſolid vertue.</p>
            <p>There followeth afterwards another conformity of moſt pure lights,
and motions, with the act of the will, and affections, purged from all ſelfe
reſpect, and veſted with the diuine will, pretending in ſuch diuine
influences only to obey Almighty God, &amp; his diuine pleaſure, and nothing
our ſelues, where with the ſoule paſſeth into God, &amp; transformeth
her ſelfe more highly, and profoundly then euer; &amp; heere ſhe offereth,
&amp; giueth, &amp; dedicateth her ſelf who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vnto God.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="chapter">
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:21191:25"/>
            <head>THE FOVRTH Degree. CHAP. VII.</head>
            <p>AFTER that the ſoule is exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed thus in purging &amp;
diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appropriating her ſelfe in theſe ſpirituall motions, and in
deſire of ſolid vertue, as hath bin ſaid: there wil follow a higher
degree which is this. It happeneth often, that hauing ſuch deſires, the
ſoule can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not attayne vnto that ſhe preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, and that for ſome
worldly, or humane cauſe which doth hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it: as for example, when we
muſt leaue prayer, by the which the ſoule findeth her ſelfe prompt, apt,
ready, and as it were inuited to vnite her ſelfe with God. And obedience on
the other ſide, or <pb n="54" facs="tcp:21191:26"/>charity requireth to leaue it for
another worke of great diſtractio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but profitable to our neighbours. And
this wilbe neceſſary not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in one worke, or at one tyme only, but it
ſhalbe needfull alſo concerning our manner of liuing, to leaue the quiet,
and contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue life, in which the ſoule felt her ſelfe greatly inflamed
with ardent deſire of ſolid vertues, to buſy her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in the
negotiations of the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue life, in which ſhe ſhall haue great repugnance,
and by which ſhe ſhall receaue many occaſions of diſtraction;
neuertheles ſhe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth clearely, that ſhe is called by God to leaue that
for this, &amp; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymes alſo ſhall find hinderances which proceed from
God, to wit, when God giueth vs not ſo quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y as we would, this vertue &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ction, which he inciteth vs to
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſire.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:21191:26"/>In the like occaſions the ſoule is
accuſtomed to feele payne, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xiety, and ſorrow, for ſuch hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derances,
and is therewith very much afflicted. It is needfull heere that ſhe
conſider, that there may be ſelfe-intereſt in this buſines, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
it be very ſecret, and hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, which ſhe ought to caſt away wholy, with
a noble and coura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious abnegation.</p>
            <p>The ſorrow then, and anxiety that afflicteth the ſoule in ſuch
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, and maketh it vnquiet, pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth ordinarily of ſelfe-loue: and although it be without
ſinne, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe it is a hinderance bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weene God, and the ſoule;
ſeeing that as a thing created, it hindereth perfectiton, and keepeth the
ſoule backe from arriuing to the top of the ſame. Alſo the propriety is
diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered plainely, although it be of a holy thing, and it ſeemeth
ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by <pb n="56" facs="tcp:21191:27"/>(althogh indirectly) that a man will giue a law
vnto God. And fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally the vnquietnes that afflicteth the ſoule inwardly, is
not of God, whoſe ſpirit is ſweet and gratious, and full of peace and
tranquility: &amp; to take away ſuch vnquietnes, he muſt forſake ſuch
deſires, &amp; the vertue it ſelfe, in the manner that followeth.</p>
            <p>Firſt a man ought to accept, &amp; receiue this deſire as a gift
of God, without reſting or ſtaying him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in his proper delight and
ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, as hath been ſayd in the degree before: and he ought to
procure with all diligence to put it in execution, neuer letting paſſe any
meanes, that he doth not try by experience, &amp; put in practice, that thereby
he may come to ſuch vertue and perfection: for ſo much as doing this, he
chaſeth far away all tepidity, &amp; negligence.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:21191:27"/>When theſe hinderances before declared happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
he ought preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to thinke that the diuine boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is not pleaſed at
that time in the execution of his deſire, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ought to renounce
it quite, with proteſtation that he will ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue neyther vertue, nor perfection
(I meane, the execution, or act of deſire only, for the ground or
eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the deſire ought to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine) but euen ſuch, and in that
manner, &amp; when God will giue it; renouncing vtterly al the reſt. He ought
then to take away all anxiety, and griefe, diſcouering plainely his ſelfe
loue, &amp; his owne intereſt, that was hid vnder ſuch deſires, although
they be holy: &amp; alſo learn this moſt high doctrine, which is, that
ſuch a deſire euen of martyrdome; with this anxiety, although it ſeeme to
be a great thing commeth to be very baſe, &amp; <pb n="58" facs="tcp:21191:28"/>little,
for ſo much as it is ſelfe-inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, &amp; a hindrance between God and
the ſoule: which being taken away, the deſire remayneth as great as euer,
and inſteed of the anxiety, it is accompanyed with a meruaylous tranquillity
in God, and in his diuine Will.</p>
            <p>And note well, that the ſoule that hath ſuch a deſire with
repoſe, &amp; tranquillity, without the vertue and perfection deſired, is
more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeeble to God then any other who hath ſuch a vertue; which if ſhe
had not receaued, or had not attayned vnto, would haue beene much grieued and
troubled, ſeeing that he obtaineth moſt perfection, who is moſt conformed
to Gods will and pleaſure, and exchangeth the vertue created, for the diuine
will increated, which doth farre ſurpaſſe, and infinitely exceed the
other: notwithſtanding the deſire <pb n="59" facs="tcp:21191:28"/>will remayne, not
with humayne feare, that afflicteth &amp; diſquieteth the ſoule, but with a
diuine feare, which is annexed neceſſarily vnto the deſire. For to
deſire a thing that we cannot haue, bringeth feare, which is acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panyed with
paine, vntill ſuch tyme as it is obtayned: but this is a paine from the which
doth proceed a meruaylous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment, and a reſignation vnto God, knowing
wel that our Lord is pleaſed greatly with ſuch a pain, to wit, to ſee a
ſoule quiet, and full of peace in her payne, to reſigne her ſelfe and
accompliſh his will, who for to pleaſe her Lord, wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly and of her own
accord, wil remaine depriued of a good, that ſhe ſo inſtantly doth
deſire, becauſe her loue vnto her Lord, is more then vnto any perfection,
or ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue.</p>
            <p>In ſuch a ſoule remaineth ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily <pb n="60" facs="tcp:21191:29"/>a
diuine light, that doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct &amp; teach her, what great dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence
ſhe ought to vſe, without <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uer
relenting, or waxing cold &amp; negligent; but a ſoule muſt not rely vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
the ſame, ſeeing ſhe doth not come to this that ſhe deſireth by her
diligence, and induſtry, how great ſoeuer it be, but by the will and
pleaſure of God, who ſometymes giueth it, &amp; ſometimes not, euen as he
beſt pleaſeth. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by reiecting, and looſing all eſteeme of our
owne diligence, &amp; induſtry, is gotten a certayne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence &amp;
filiall ſecurity, that God, who hath giuen the deſire, will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo giue
the perfection, when he ſhall pleaſe, and according to his will. And thus
for his owne part, the ſoule putteth, and caſteth her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe as a little
infant into his ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, and is moſt contented with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, thinking no more of
it, but <pb n="61" facs="tcp:21191:29"/>with a pure &amp; ſincere reſignation vnto God,
worketh as out of her ſelfe, and, as we may ſay, at ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture leaueth all
care of her ſelfe to our Lord, as a little infant, with a kind of diuine
tranquillity.</p>
            <p>To this ſo high renunciation, and diſappropriation doth
correſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pond the ſubtractio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or withdraw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of our Lord already ſpoken
of, when he doth not giue the vertue we demand, which we ought to admit with
ioy, and cooperate in the manner aforeſayd. Alſo there is diſcouered
clearely a conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty with the diuine will, very ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret, and knowne but
vnto few, ſeeing that man leaueth God for God, that is to ſay, leaueth and
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth God, in as much as he bringeth any ſelfe intereſt with ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e, and perfection, to hau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> him more excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly, to wit, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
any intereſt. From whence <pb n="62" facs="tcp:21191:30"/>followeth a moſt high
tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>sforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and an admirable Deificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, from which is accuſtomed to
proceed excellent gifts, and very rare lights, worthy of ſuch a loue, and
ſo great vnion with God.</p>
            <p>In particuler the aforeſayd do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine ought to be applied to three
ſorts of deſires, beſides the place it hath in all others. The firſt is
of eternall glory, in which ſhe ought to be reſigned in the manner be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
ſpecifyed, when our Lord de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferreth it, eſteeming much more of the diuine
will, to the end ſhe might entierly forſake al ſelf loue, althogh it be
of the moſt excellent good that is.</p>
            <p>The ſecond is, the deſire of this anihilation, renou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cing of her
ſelfe the conformity with God, which ſhe muſt alſo moderate with the
ſelfe ſame rule aforeſayd, when our Lord doth not giue it ſo much as 
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:21191:30"/>ſhe would: where it is well to be noted, that to
forſake willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the loue of the ſame vertue, which is with anxiety, and
ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous propriety, for the deſire to haue the ſame vertue with
ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and be content to beare the burthen of her imperfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
againſt her will, &amp; to conforme her ſelfe wholy vnto Gods will, is a
moſt great renunciation, and ſurpaſſeth all other vertues. And here
muſt be taken away the anxiety, &amp; griefe that we haue to obtaine it:
&amp; note well, that the more diligence we ſhall vſe with anxiety, and
pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety, for to obtaine it of God, the leſſe ſhall we haue it.</p>
            <p>The third is the deſire of ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, althogh our nature
repugn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, as a thing contrary to
ſenſe: it may happen neuertheleſſe, that the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to haue it, is
too great by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of anxiety, and ſelfe loue in
<gap reason="missing" resp="#OXF" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:21191:31"/>and
indure, taketh away ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment, and hindreth the perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of
operatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s; the ſoule ought to take away, &amp; cut off the thoghts of
croſſes, and paynes, when it is not time to ſuffer, conuerting and
changing all into this cherefulnes of conformity with God, to the which, the
thinking of pleaſant and delightfull things (ſo they be holy) helpeth much,
for that ſuch thinges are conformable to perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            <p>Of this cherefulnes ſpringeth a promptnes to all operations,
ſtrength to ſurmount difficulties, and ioy of hart &amp; vnderſtanding,
as the Apoſtle ſayth: <hi>Gaudete in Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mino ſemper, iterum dico
gaudete:</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce in our Lord alwaies, againe I ſay reioice. Agility
alſo to take in hand any good worke, facility to execute and end it, and
ſweetnes in all things, euen in the croſſe it <pb n="67" facs="tcp:21191:31"/>ſelfe, when it is taken only for the loue of God, and to pleaſe
him. And if we haue not ſuch cheerful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, at the leaſt we ought to
deſire it, and inforce our ſelues to haue it in reſiſting al
hinderances that the diuell ſhall oppoſe.</p>
            <p>Our Lord was ſingularly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued with this alacrity, and ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
it in his countenance, rendring himſelfe very amiable, whereby is manifeſt
that he thought not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes on his paſſion, but that he diuerted and
retired his mind and thoughts, except when he knew that it was the will of his
Father he ſhould; and thought on ioyfull things with a pleaſant aſpect,
and with a ſweet and gracious counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, accompanyed with gra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ity and words of weight, to draw th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> harts of the people with mild<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> and authority; and with this al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crity he indured, and ſuffered af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards <pb n="68" facs="tcp:21191:32"/>the ſubtraction, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of it away, in the tyme of his paſſion.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="chapter">
            <head>THE FIFTH Degree. CHAP. VIII.</head>
            <p>THE ſoule being in this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity, tranquillity, and cheerfulnes
which hath byn ſayd, with progreſſe in perfect vertues, and with great
power of the ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>our part ouer
the inf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>riour, by reaſon of the
long habit, and great facility ſhe hath gotten in repreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, and
ſubduing the motions of her paſſions; God is wont after this, or when he
thinketh good, to permit her to begim to feel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> great tentations, the li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, or grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then thoſe which ſhe ſuffered in the beginning
of her co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſion, to wit, of the fleſh, of impatience, <pb n="69" facs="tcp:21191:32"/>of feare, of difficultyes, and other the like, in ſuch ſort, that
ſhe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginneth agayne to feele a great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion in her inferior part
againſt the ſuperiour, &amp; the diuel ſharply tempteth her, in ſo much
that ſhe is forced to returne to fight, &amp; that with great difficulty: but
notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, the ſuperiour part gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly fighteth, gayneth, and
bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth away the victory.</p>
            <p>This mutation and vnexpected change reſembleth the imperfect
ſtate of a nouice, or beginner on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. The rebellions of the inferiour part
agaynſt the ſuperiour, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentations of diuells, the moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of
ſenſuality, &amp; the newnes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>accuſtomed, are as it were againſt the
common ſtile of grace, that happeneth to vs ordinarily after the firſt
aſſaultes of temptations, &amp; the victory ouer them, hauing gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the
habits of perfect vertues, <pb n="70" facs="tcp:21191:33"/>and in ſuch ſort ſubdued
ſenſuali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that ſcarcely it dare once kicke or repugne. All theſe
things are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed to put the ſoule in great perill, of thinking ſhe
goeth back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and that ſhe hath giuen oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of her being in ſo
euill an eſtate, whereby is wont to riſe in her mind vnquietnes,
deſpayre, &amp; great decay of wonted force: and therfore it behooueth that
ſhe ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d well vpon her guard, and before all thinges conſider and
obſerue, that the will, by the grace of God is reſolute, rather to dye a
thouſand tymes, then to offend God in the leaſt thing that is. And for that
ſin conſiſteth in the will, ſhe ought alſo firmely to perſwade her
ſelfe, that ſhe is farre from committing of it, ſeeing that all her
griefe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth of thoſe contrary motions, her will being ſo earneſtly
bent, not to offend God. And which is <pb n="71" facs="tcp:21191:33"/>more, ſhe ought to
be ſecure, that ſhe hath not on her part giuen oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions to ſuch
tentations, ſeing that ſhe abhorreth, and deteſteth them greatly: and
principally for that ſhe deſireth to conforme her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe altogeather to
the diuine wil, and to diſappropriate herſelfe of al thinges created. She
muſt likewiſe be aduertiſed, that ſhe doth per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme this while diuers
actes of vertue with the ſuperiour part, for ſo much as hereby through
diuine grace the ſpirit is made more vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorous, although the fleſh be
mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and incumbred with no ſmall perturbations, and this ſo much the
more, for that ſhe ſhall find manifeſtly &amp; aſſuredly, that there
is no offence therin: and if ſhe find that ſhe cannot ſufficiently
reſolue her ſelfe, for her continuall feares, and remorſe of
conſcience, let her remit her ſelfe, and repoſe wholy <pb n="72" facs="tcp:21191:34"/>on the iudgment of him, that hath the guiding of her ſoule.</p>
            <p>Moreouer ſhe muſt be aduerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, that ſuch temptations,
althogh they ſeeme vnto her to be the ſame that ſhe was wont to endure in
the beginning, are notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding very much different, if ſhe conſider
the cauſe from whence they proceed: for that then the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour part being
deſtitute of good habits, vertues and graces that giue great ſtrength, and
the inferiour part full of euill habits, very ſtrong and ſtubborne,
togea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the fraudulent ſleights of the diuell concurring therin, no
meruayle that the fleſh did fight and rebell againſt the ſpirit, vntill
ſuch tyme as the ſuperiour part were made ſtrong and vigorous, and our
Lord giuing ſtrength to reſiſt, and vanquiſh the inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our part; which
being thus tamed, <pb n="73" facs="tcp:21191:34"/>the battayle ceaſeth ſoone after,
with a ſubmiſſion and tranquilli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity betweene the one and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;
our Lord permitting al this, to the end, that by the way of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat, to his
imitation, we may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne the victory, and alſo by this meanes be made
partakers of his celeſtiall gifts and vertues.</p>
            <p>But when after all this the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations returne, the ſoule being
al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready fortified, and not hauing gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen any occaſion thereunto, the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhe muſt aſſuredly know, that
this is an expreſſe prouidence of God, who will haue it ſo, and that
ſuch temptations doe not take their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the interiour, to wit, of
default that is in her, but come of other cauſes: and this great and
ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret inſtruction helpeth much to what end our Lord worketh and
permitteth all this. For firſt it is to the end, that the repoſe and peace 
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:21191:35"/>that ſhe had before, be not occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to her of ſo
great ſatisfaction, and contentment that ſhe come to delight much in
herſelfe for it, &amp; ſo be in da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger to fall into pride. Secondly, that
ſelfe-loue which ſubtilly vſeth oftentymes to enter therein, be quite
extinguiſhed. Thirdly, that there may increaſe, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue in the
ſoule the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege of her baſenes &amp; little worth. Fourthly, that ſhe
may attayne to a new light, and know that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection doth not conſiſt in
being free from temptations and in ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing peace betweene ſenſuality &amp;
reaſon: for it may ſo fall out, that theſe temptations wil be more
ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hement, then thoſe that ſhe had before, and that ſhe ſhall ſuffer
much by them, and therefore ſhe ought to hold her ſelf aſſured, that
our Lord by ſuch meanes will bring her to greater vertue.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:21191:35"/>Wherfore when ſhe beginneth to enter into
ſuch afflictions or troubles ſhe ought before al things to humble her
ſelfe &amp; deſcend into her owne nothing, and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge herſelfe
worthy of all temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations: and in the ſame manner, as ſhe was already
before accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, to receyne with contentme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t the contempt and afflictions
out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly: ſo ought ſhe to inforce herſelfe to reioice in that our Lord
is pleaſed to humble her, and to permit her thus to be buffeted of the
diuell. Secondly ſhe ought to be willing to want the peace and repoſe that
ſhe felt when ſhe had no great temptations, and likewiſe all the
contentment which ſhe had therein. And how much the more ſuch repoſe is a
high and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent good, ſo much the greater ſacrifice it is, &amp; more
pleaſing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, to be willingly depriued <pb n="76" facs="tcp:21191:36"/>thereof for
the l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ue of him.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, ſhe ought to admit with the ſame affection, and
promptnes, as is ſpoken of before, the ſubtraction or withdrawing that our
Lord doth vſe, which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth in this, that he doth not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the
vertue or power of the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour part, to redound &amp; worke in the
inferiour, by giuing it ſuch force as that it ſhold not feele theſe
temptations: (which would be, if God did concurre therein as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore:) but our
Lord withdraweth ſuch concourſe, and from hence proceedeth anxiety and
affliction. Fourthly ſhe ought not to inforce herſelfe to d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ue away theſe temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations with
great pennance and mortification of nature, as ſhe did at the b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ginning when ſhe was a No<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ce, for by that way (as is read of
ſome Saints) the temptations increaſe rather then otherwiſe, but 
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:21191:36"/>ſhe ought to ſubmit herſelfe vnto God with humility,
for to ſuffer them willingly, as long as it is in his will &amp; pleaſure,
and then not to care for them, but to contemne them.</p>
            <p>Afterwardes, of this followeth the conformity to the diuine will
greater then euer, ſeeing that to conforme her ſelfe vnto him, the ſoule
is content to be left comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, and to ſuffer ſuch paine and
confuſion, which is moſt pleaſing to his diuine maieſty: beſides
that, it is very co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>formable to that which our Redeemer did, when being in the
garden he would that the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour part ſhould find difficulty to ſuffer,
&amp; neuertheleſſe he ſaid, <hi>non mea, ſed tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> voluntas fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t,</hi> not my will (o Father) but thine be done. And of this
conformity riſeth in the ſoule not only a loue of vnion that tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s formeth
it into God more <pb n="78" facs="tcp:21191:37"/>highly, but alſo a loue and deſire of
the croſſe, in conformity with our Sauiour, when as to acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pliſh the
diuine will, ſhe is content to ſuffer temptation. And heere ſhe doth not
only offer, and dedicate herſelfe vnto God, but doth alſo ſacrifice
herſelfe vnto him.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="chapter">
            <head>THE SIXT Degree. CHAP. IX.</head>
            <p>BESIDES all this that hath beene ſayd, the affliction and payne is
accuſtomed to paſſe fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and come euen to the ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our part
where vertue and ſpirit make their reſidence. And ſo ſhe ſhall
perceaue her ſelfe to fayle &amp; want light in her vnderſtanding, and good
purpoſes, and deſires in her affections, promptnes to doe well, ſtrength
and patience &amp; the <pb n="79" facs="tcp:21191:37"/>like, in ſuch ſort, as where
before ſhe did fight with great force and vigour, now it will ſeeme vnto
her, that ſhe is without ſtrength and vertue, and that ſhe cannot
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt, and euery little ſtraw will ſeeme vnto her a blocke, and ſo
ſhall feele and perceaue nothing but obſcurity, and blindnes, great
darkenes, aridity or drineſſe, grief, tepidity, rebellion, puſillanimity,
confuſion and great oppreſſion, ſeeming vnto her vnpoſſible to
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to her firſt deſignementes &amp; good purpoſes. And heere in
very truth is great danger, if ſhe do not inforce herſelfe to remedy it as
ſhe ſhould, to the end ſhe fall not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſundry great inconueniences,
whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhe is thus abandoned, which happeneth in diuers manners.</p>
            <p>Firſt in apprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding too firme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly all this that hath beene
ſpoken of, to be a great miſery, &amp; for this <pb n="80" facs="tcp:21191:38"/>cauſe
afflicting her ſelfe, &amp; grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſad. Secondly, too earneſt
ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting her ſelfe to thinke of what cauſe they proceed, attributing all
to her owne defaults, and infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing herſelfe to look curiouſly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them.
Thirdly, of ſet purpoſe, procuring with great diligence to free herſelfe
of them, to take order to remedy all, and returne to her firſt eſtate,
eſteeming the preſent to be miſerable, and yet neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe
leeſing all this labour: for this being not the true way, nor the remedy of
her euill, ſhe findeth the trouble to be thereby increaſed. Fourthly, for
this cauſe, the ſoule is accuſtomed to fall into impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, feare, and
puſillanimity &amp; in danger to deſpayre, it ſeeming vnto her that
nothing doth help her, and that ſhe goeth from euill to worſe. Suppoſing
the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſoule to be exerciſed in theſe foreſayd <pb n="81" facs="tcp:21191:38"/>degrees, it is needfull ſhe conſider with her ſelfe, &amp;
principally with the help of him that guideth her, the ſecret and me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uaylous myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries that are hidden herein. For the
firſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, let her know that the true cauſe of all that is ſayd, is the
di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine prouidence, who willing to make proofe, and to purify a ſoule, after
he hath enriched her with ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, and great ſtrength in the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iour part, is wont to retire his
accuſtomed ſuccours, without the which theſe vertues cannot work: whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>of it commeth, that although ſhe haue
them, yet do they ſeeme to her that ſhe hath them not: and from hence
followeth darkenes, aridity, and other miſeries already ſpoken off;
notwithſtanding the graces and foreſayd vertues remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in the ſoule
as before.</p>
            <p>For the ſecond, this ſubtraction or diuine withdrawing doth not 
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:21191:39"/>proceed of the abſence of vertues, giftes, and graces,
ſeeing that they remayne entierly in the ſoule, &amp; it doth leſſe
proceed from the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for ſo much as indeed the ſoule is
depriued thereof. But we muſt conſider that in internal and ſpirituall
actions, there is a direct act, that tendeth directly to God, to wit, the
ſame internall act or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration touching his obiect: as for example, the
practicall know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and election, or lawfull de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, to haue a wil to
ſuffer, to haue a will to loue God, to haue a will to be temperate, chaſt,
obedient, not to conſent vnto ſin &amp;c. There is alſo the act
reflectiue, that tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to wardes it ſelfe, to wit, to diſcerne &amp;
iudge whether he doth ſuch an act, whereby he may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue contentment, and
reioyce therein for the glory of God, for that he diſcerneth himſelfe by
the <pb n="83" facs="tcp:21191:39"/>ſame to be ſtrong, and victorious ouer temptations,
with great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of the ſoule.</p>
            <p>Of theſe two, the firſt is the pure act of vertue: the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d
is the fruit that redoundeth in vs, &amp; the fruition of the ſame vertue:
&amp; this is moſt cleare that the act of tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance doth not conſiſt to
per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue that he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ath it, or to
reioyce in it, or content himſelfe therein, but to deſire it, and
effectuate it. Now God concurreth in the firſt, and by that meanes the acts
of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue are performed, but he with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draweth the ſecond, to wit, our
knowledge, reflection, iudgment, and ſatisfaction to haue done the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and
therfore it ſeemeth to vs, that we do them not, &amp; in the place of the
knowledge withdrawne, hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth darknes &amp; blindnes, in place of the ioyfull
affection ſucceedeth aridity &amp; dryneſſe: euen as it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth 
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:21191:40"/>to him that is almoſt ſtarued, who receyuing food into
his ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke neyther feeleth nor taſteth it: it is cleare that he eateth,
and notwithſtanding it ſeemeth vnto him he eateth not, and hath in a manner
no more ſatisfaction of ſuch an act, then if he had not done it. Seeing
then that it is not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly vertue to perceaue our inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour actions, and
that therin doth not conſiſt vertuous effects and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perations, being only
ſatisfaction vnto our ſelues, our Lord preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to bereaue vs of all our
pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per taſt &amp; intereſt, as a hinderance betwixt him &amp; vs. leaueth
vs the purity of vertue, which is no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing but to deſire it, &amp; put
it in effect, and taketh away the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, which is a certayne ſelfeloue
more ſubtile then thoſe that haue yet beene ſpecifyed, &amp; an
intereſt with the which the ſoule nouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth <pb n="85" facs="tcp:21191:40"/>it
ſelfe, and ſuch as diuerteth vs from greater vnion with God: and this being
ſo, it is plainely to be ſeene, that there is not only no euill heerin, nor
any danger to be feared, but that the ſoule by ſuch a diuine work is
purifed the more in vertue, and is purged from all proprieties, and ſelfe
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, although it be very hidden, and is rayſed to a degree, and
diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of greater grace, &amp; much more vnion with God then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.
For to make all this mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, the ſoule that is come to this eſtate,
muſt be aduertiſed of two pointes. The firſt, that if ſhe will examine
the purity of vertue, ſhe ſhall ſee the ſame in her actions more then
euer ſhe did. For if one ſhould demaund of her in theſe griefes,
obſcurities and rebellions, if ſhe would offend God, ſhe would
preſently anſwere, that <gap reason="missing" resp="#OXF" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:21191:41"/>Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, of whom it is written in the
beginning of his dolorous paſſion: <hi>Coepit pauere,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere, &amp; moeſtus
eſſe;</hi> that is to ſay, he began to be troubled, to feare, and became
ſad: and after he ſaid, <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtis eſt anima mea vſque ad
mortem,</hi> my ſoule is ſorrowfull euen vnto death. Now we muſt
conſider three pointes. Firſt the greatnes of the paine &amp; torments that
he was preſently to endure. Secondly that then was with drawne from him the
concurrence of ſtrength, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, magnanimity, &amp; the like vertues,
concerning the feeling of them in the manner aforeſaid, and for that cauſe
he prese<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly fell into ſo great anguiſh, feare, &amp; heauines, that the
leaſt of his ſorrowes ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med vnto him inſupportable, wherof before he
reioiced ſo much in thinking of them, ſaying: <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> hab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> baptizari, &amp; qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>do c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arctor <pb n="89" facs="tcp:21191:41"/>vſque dum
perfici<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tur:</hi> I haue to be
baptized with a Baptiſme, &amp; how am I ſtraitened vntill it be
diſpatched. Thirdly, that with all this, the ſtedfaſtnes of vertue was
moſt firme &amp; more ſtable the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euer, ſeeing that in theſe words to
his Apoſtles, <hi>Surgite, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>amu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> ariſe, let
vs go (that is, to meet them that came to apprehend him) he diſcouered a
meru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ilous promptnes to ſuffer,
patience, ſtrength, and a genero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of hart, not to be ouercome or
quailed by ſuch a withdrawing or ſubtraction before mentioned<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> by which the holy Doctors ſay, that
our Lord merited then for the holy Martyrs &amp; other Saints, who in their
torments and paines were ſo richly armed with patien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, ſtrength,
magnanimity &amp; other vertues in the ſuperiour part, that by the ſame
vertues they did ſo triumph, &amp; reioyce euen in the <pb n="90" facs="tcp:21191:42"/>middeſt of their paines &amp; torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, as we read of many holy
Martyrs. When the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, it ſhall pleaſe our Lord to take away, &amp; bereaue a
ſoule, for the loue he beares it, of this garment, with the foreſaid
ſubtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, or withdrawing, as he doth in this eſtate; then it is cleare,
that he bringeth her to a higher imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of himſelfe, then was the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
ſeeing that the ſame ſubtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction was vſed to him by his eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall
Father.</p>
            <p>And beſides this reaſon of the moſt liuely imitation of our
Lord there followeth others alſo, to wit, that how much the ſuperior part
is more noble then the inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, or then the body: ſo much more the
ſuffering of it, or both together, is more noble then any martyrdome
whatſoeuer of body only, if it be without the other. And moreouer to ſuffer
with this <pb n="91" facs="tcp:21191:42"/>fredom &amp; liberty, or ſenſible force of
vertue, with which the Martyrs were indued was as eaſye vnto them, as if they
had bene in the middeſt of roſes. But with this ſubtractio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or
withdrawing it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth not only difficult, but alſo impoſſible. So
that with all this difficulty to be thus magnani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous, and couragious with all
ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficacy, maketh vs more apt, and prepared for higher vertue, and greater
merit. And finally to find our ſelues ſo freely &amp; highly ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vnto
vertue, naturally it is an occaſion of perill &amp; danger of pride: wherfore
vnto <hi>S Paul</hi> (<hi>Ne magnitudo reuelationum extelleret eum,</hi>
leaſt the greatnes of his reuelatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſhould extoll him) there was giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to
preſerue him the temptation of the fleſh, ſo to counterpoiſe the
daunger which might follow: by this height of vertue the ſoule is 
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:21191:43"/>plunged into this extreme low eſtate, by the feeling
which ſhe hath of troubles &amp; feares &amp;c. And therfore ſhe is
ſecure, that is, ſhe is preſerued from danger, which is a ſigne of
higher eſtate, for that ſhe hath a great foundation of humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and
knowledg of her owne baſenes. This as it ſeemeth, may be gathered of the
temptation of <hi>S. Paul,</hi> which was giuen him for auoyding the perill
wherin he was: wherof it followeth, that the hauing of that temptation of the
fleſh, was a higher eſtate, then the firſt, ſeeing that by this mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
the hinderances and imperfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of the firſt are taken away. and he is
made more ſecure ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, in ſuch ſort, as this eſtate is a certaine
probation, that God ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of his elect, a liuely imitation of our Lord and
Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, a more excellent Martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, <pb n="93" facs="tcp:21191:43"/>then the exteriour, &amp; foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vpon profound humility, which is
more ſure then any other whatſoeuer, and is of greater me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and a
diſpoſition to receiue greater gifts &amp; graces, &amp; which is more, an
enemy to proper loue; for that it taketh away the ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and
contentment that is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued of vertues, and ſo by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence
increaſeth, &amp; commeth to be of greater conformity with the diuine will,
&amp; is enkindled more in loue towards God, then the others before mentioned:
ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that for to ſatisfy Almighty God, a man depriueth himſelfe of
ſo great a good, and remayneth with the pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e actes of vertues, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked of all ſenſible ornaments, and
ſelfe contentment.</p>
            <p>That which ought after war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des to be practiſed, is: Firſt for
ſo much as the diuell is wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <pb n="94" facs="tcp:21191:44"/>the ſoule
with many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghtes, as if all this happened for ſome great defaults, that
were in her (which afflicteth her much:) to deliuer her ſelfe from this,
ſhe ought to repent herſelf of all her defects, ſinnes, and occaſions
that ſhe may haue giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in this caſe, but in generall, without any more
thinking therof; and the reſt, to remit herſelfe wholy vnto her Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour,
belieuing in all things his aduiſe, and renouncing her owne iudgment, keeping
her ſelfe in peace, and repoſe of conſcience, ſuppoſing this maxime,
which is greatly neceſſary in this ſixt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, to wit, that a man ought
not to iudge of himſelfe, nor of what he feeleth in himſelfe, ſeing that
that the ſubtraction maketh that he can haue no light, reflection, nor
perfect iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of his actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s; but he ought to content himſelfe, 
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:21191:44"/>and reioyce in this darknes, and a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>idity, and ought to humble and ſubmit himſelf to the
iudgment of another, anihilating &amp; acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging himſelfe worthy of
this, and ſo much worſe, vnworthy of all light, and in ſuch baſenes he
ought to glorify God.</p>
            <p>Although that the motions of impatience, and other the like
na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall motions be great, and make the ſoule to become ſad and
me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy, without feeling any comfort, or ſolace; yet muſt ſhe know,
and labour for, &amp; to trie by experience, the for ſaid ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,
which doth alſo conſiſt in reſigning, &amp; remitting her ſelf wholy
vnto God, euen as one that is ſick, who althogh he cry throgh the vehemency
of his paines, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe in will, is ſubmitted entirely vnto God,
and is content to ſuffer any thing.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:21191:45"/>As for feare &amp; puſillanimity (beſides
that which naturally ſhe feeleth, which is not euil of it ſelf) ſhe ought
not to admit any more, not to conſent vnto it, but ought to endeauour
herſelf to performe acts of ſubmiſſion, confidence in God, familiarity,
&amp; the like.</p>
            <p>And doing all this that is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue ſaid, and with the ſame,
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying herſelf in all things, and conforming herſelfe vnto God, not
willing any thing, but what he willeth, if ſhe feele theſe trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, and
darknes to increaſe, ſhe muſt not for all that, be afflicted for any
thing whatſoeuer it be; but without any kind of murmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, ſhe muſt
ſeeke to forget her euill, &amp; ought to know that God is accuſtomed to
doe this: that is to ſay, to withdraw all conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and help in our
temptations. Therfore ſhe muſt then redouble <pb n="97" facs="tcp:21191:45"/>her
conformity &amp; thanksgiuing vnto God, and quiet herſelfe, and repoſe with
aſſurance that in the end God will not leaue her, not permit that ſhe be
tempted about her ſtrength, which heere doth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſt wholy in
reſiſtance againſt them, or putting them away, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that is not ſo
much in our power by reaſon of the ſubtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: but in this, to ſuffer
and ſupport them; &amp; this is more ſure &amp; perfect, then extaſy.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="chapter">
            <head>OF THE SECOND Eſtate. CHAP. X.</head>
            <p>VVHo would thinke, that there ſhold be any thing yet left in the
Soule which ſhe might renounce, forſake &amp; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw her ſelfe from,
beſides this that hath bene ſaid, &amp; eſpecially <pb n="98" facs="tcp:21191:46"/>the ſoule being brought to the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pure and direct act of vertue,
in the which it ſeemeth there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but true vertue, &amp; alſo
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaued of all proper intereſt. But if we conſider that ſuch an act
al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it be thus purged, is a pure act of election, and of our will, the
which, with his actiue vertue imperatiue, in reſpect of the other powers,
worketh and produceth the acts of vertue; it cannot be denyed, but that there
is proper will, and intereſt therin, although much purged, and by
conſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce there is ſomwhat yet to forſake, and to be purged.</p>
            <p>The ſoule then that is left without any other action but to doe in
the manner aboue explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, being ariued to the foreſaid ſixt degree, our
Lord is accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to withdraw by little, and little, the power to do ſuch
actes, <pb n="99" facs="tcp:21191:46"/>taking now one, now another vntill ſuch tyme, that
indeed he taketh away all, except the power to conforme her ſelfe vnto the
di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine will. And by experience it is proued, that ſomtymes the ſoule
findeth her ſelfe ſo oppreſſed with griefes and afflictions, and
aſſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with ſo many diſtractions, &amp; miſeries, that willing to
enforce herſelfe, yet ſhe cannot performe any act, neyther of tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes
giuing towards God, nor of fortitude, nor of patience, nor of any other vertue,
no not ſo much as to will that which is aggreable vnto God. And ſhe muſt
remaine in this ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferance, pierced through inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie with a thouſand
temptations: ſo that as the Martyrs could not defend themſelues, from their
tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments &amp; wounds, but receiuing them, conformed themſelues to the
diuine will; euen ſo muſt the <pb n="100" facs="tcp:21191:47"/>ſoule doe in this
caſe, in whom it may be, there remayneth not any actiue force, but only the
paſſiue, enduring all for the loue of God, and remaining content with the
ſame.</p>
            <p>But which is more, he is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed alſo to take away ſuch an
act of conforming herſelfe to the diuine will, in ſuch manner, that ſhe
hath not any ſenſible fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to do it, &amp; alſo leſſe can ſhe
execute it<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and there remayneth no
other thing; but a paſſiue tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillity, by which, as a lambe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the
ſhearer, ſhe remaineth quiet, and ſuffereth God to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh
whatſoeuer he pleaſeth.</p>
            <p>This is an entire and abſolute ſubtraction of the actiue power
of the ſoule, to wit, that God with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draweth in ſuch ſort his diuine
concurrence that the ſoule cam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot
in the ſuperiour part, how holy <pb n="101" facs="tcp:21191:47"/>or raiſed ſoeuer
ſhe be, make any actiue operations, but only can remaine peaceable, &amp;
quiet, endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring willingly that which God permitteth to happen vnto her.</p>
            <p>To ſuch a withdrawing the ſoule ought to be correſpondent with
anihilating and acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging herſelfe to be pure nothing, and full of
infinit ſinnes, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vnworthy to performe any action of vertue: and
ſhe ought to reioyce in ſuch contempt, that God worketh in her, taking from
her the power to lift her hart vp vnto him, with a free renuncia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; ſhe
ought to be contented to want wholy the actiue, and all the acts of vertue; the
which how much more they were pure, ſo much greater is the gift that God
imparteth therin. After this it of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten happeneth, that the troubles and
afflictions will be not only as <pb n="102" facs="tcp:21191:48"/>before, but much greater,
for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing loſt the rampire and fortreſſe of the actes of vertue: and
more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer in the concupiſcible and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour part, there wilbe raiſed
motions ſo vehement and diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, that ſhe neuer felt the like in her
life, in ſuch ſort, as it will ſeeme vnto her, that ſhe is euen in hell
it ſelfe: and heere ſhe muſt not arme herſelfe with any other ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour,
then with ſubmiſſion and paſſiue tranquillity in ſupporting all to
ſatisfy almighty God, who will haue it ſo. And ſhe ought to know, that
ſuch ſubmiſſion and tranquillity giueth to the ſoule a very great
ſtrength, not actiue but paſſiue, by the which he giueth and leaueth
herſelfe to be as a prey vnto God; and ſo like a moſt pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient lambe
ſuffereth all, in great debility &amp; feeblenes. Of this peace and
tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quillity followeth a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity <pb n="103" facs="tcp:21191:48"/>with the actiue will,
al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though paſſiue, but without com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon greater then the foreſaid,
and an inexplicable deification in an act yet paſſiue, not of oblation, nor
of gift, dedication, or holo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſt, but much more excellent &amp; more
perfect, as to giue themſelu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
wholy, as it were a prey vnto al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God.</p>
            <p>In this eſtate ſhe muſt be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertiſed of ſome things of
much importance: one is, that the inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour, and imperatiue actions of vertue
are not loſt, but are made more actiue then euer, in ſuch fort that a
perſon hath ſtrength to worke and exerciſe the partes and powers of her
body and ſoule in ſpeaking, thinking, and doing, all that is conuenient to
be done, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to her vocation, yea euen in performing acts of temperance,
patience &amp;c. Alſo when ſhe ought <pb n="104" facs="tcp:21191:49"/>to ayd and help
her neighbour, it is with the accuſtomed affability: for the act of
commaundment, &amp; practice reſteth in the ſoule, to commaund, and to
direct all her actions of commaund or execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. For the ſubtraction, or
with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing ought to bee vnderſtood in the vnderſtanding and will,
concerning the proper interiour acts of the will, intention, fruitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
election, reioycing, ſatiſfaction, &amp; the like, which indeed are ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
away.</p>
            <p>Another is, that it muſt not be vnderſtood, that our Lord
ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth away the gifts, or habits, but the acts, not giuing his help &amp;
concurrence, notwithſtanding he doth not ſo alwaies: for that often in this
eſtate, he letteth the ſoule be free, and at liberty to worke, but
ſometymes he ſuſpendeth it, and this is done without any cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine 
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:21191:49"/>rule, and when he pleaſeth. Therfore the ſoule ought
to be wholy reſigned, to be depriued of all acts, or not, as much, and when
it ſhall pleaſe God, and to be alwaies ready to renounce the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with this
admirable indifferency. When the actiue is taken away in ſhe manner
aforeſaid, then the ſoule remaineth in the paſſiue ſtate in two
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orts. Firſt, for that with
promp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nes, &amp; great
tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillity ſhe ſubmitteth herſelfe to all the afflictions, and
foreſaid troubles, and miſeries, induring them moſt willingly, although
ſhe be tranſpierced, and wounded by them, for the great reſolution ſhe
hath made rather to ſuffer a thouſand deaths, then to offend God, and for
that ſhe ſuffereth ſo many euill motions: and alſo for that ſhe
cannot performe any act of vertue, but only ſuffereth ſuch 
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:21191:50"/>affliction for the loue of God.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the ſoule in ſuch eſtate being retyred to the
deepeſt part of her hart, (which the My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall Deuines call <hi>Pax
anima,</hi> the peace of the ſoule) operatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> being withdrawne, ſhe giueth
and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitteth herſelf with great pro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes vnto God, who worketh within
with the paſſiue conſent of her freewill, much more higher acts, then of
thanks-giuing, loue, vnion with him, election, or any other vertue, without
taſt; only admitting them, and cooperating with all her hart, and affection,
in ſuch ſort, that as the vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding retyred from the ſenſe in
ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſy cannot be attentiue with her naturall forces to actiue vertues, as
ſhe was before, but receiueth di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine light, that worketh moſt high
vnderſtanding &amp; knowledg in her (which the myſticall Deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes 
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:21191:50"/>call <hi>pati diuina:</hi>) now if in the vnderſtanding
rayſed aboue her naturall forces, our Lord wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth this, the ſame may be
done, much more in the will, when re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing wholy the actiue, ſhe
forſaketh the ſame, &amp; then our Lord raiſing it into an extaſy,
&amp; a moſt vertuous practiſe, worketh in her entirely what he pleaſeth:
and this <hi>pati diuina,</hi> which is an eſtate much higher then the
fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, for that extaſy of the vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding is dangerous, and few
at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine vnto it, full of infinite occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and ſubiects of curioſity,
&amp; propriety: but heere the will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth and humbleth herſelfe, and
with a moſt aſſured confide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ſubmitteth herſelfe vnto God: and of
ſuch an extaſy all are capable, and it is much higher then the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
rendring the ſoule moſt ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greable and pleaſing vnto God.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="11" type="chapter">
            <pb n="108" facs="tcp:21191:51"/>
            <head>OF THE THIRD and laſt Eſtate. CHAP. XI.</head>
            <p>FINALLY our Lord is accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to take away not only the actiue,
but alſo the foreſaid paſſiue, the will remayning in all, and by all,
naked and impotent for any thing. It is true, ſhe doth not reſiſt, or
oppoſe her ſelfe to this, but ſhe ſuffereth herſelfe to be bereaued
of all. And for the vnderſtanding of this laſt Eſtate, which is the
higheſt of all the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, it muſt be noted, that the vertue and force of
the liberty which the will hath, is ſo great, that ſhe can renounce wholy
her will, and wholy her liberty, and indeed bereaueth herſelfe of them, as if
ſhe neuer had them; and ſhe doth this freely with her good 
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:21191:51"/>will: and by ſuch a renunciation the will is made as it
were no wil, in the like manner, as <hi>S. Pauli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> made himſelfe a ſlaue to deliuer another
ſlaue: euen ſo the ſoule hath power to doe with her inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour, and with
her free will and liberty.</p>
            <p>Then our Lord taketh away the actiue, and the paſſiue by
ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction, and all acts whatſoeuer, as if ſhe were not at all: and
ſhe doth not reſiſt this, but with an entire exhibition of ſuch a
renun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciation, concurring therwith, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to be no practicall will, to wit,
that all the operations that ſhe doth, or can doe concerning herſelfe,
ſhe doth not will them, nor doth them as of herſelf: yet willing them
neuertheleſſe with a will conformable to the diuine will, in which ſort
ſhe willeth &amp; worketh them; and therfore ſhe <pb n="110" facs="tcp:21191:52"/>doth
them as commaunded im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly by the diuine will, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out bringing therin any
concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of her owne, putting the will of God in the place of hers.</p>
            <p>For in as a large &amp; ſpacious Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, of the which one only
is mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, when he is abſent, he lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth ſome friend of his,
abſolute mayſter, and there is done all, that was done before, but only by
the commaundement of the friend, &amp; not of the other: euen ſo the will
renouncing it ſelfe wholy, aſwell in the actiue as in the paſſiue,
al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though pure, &amp; holy, not willing but what God willeth; and now not
willing indeed neyther more nor leſſe, to haue this ſatisfaction, as is
afore ſayd, ſhe renounceth in all thinges, and wholy the ſayd actiue and
paſſiue, being reſolued not to worke at all, as with her will,
notwithſtanding ſhe doth al <pb n="111" facs="tcp:21191:52"/>euen as before, but as
thinges willed &amp; ordeyned by God, not of herſelfe, leauing entirely &amp;
imediatly to the good pleaſure of God, the commaundment of her body, ſoule,
actions, motions, and feelings, as if truely ſhe had no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of will: and
to this God cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondeth as is ſayd, with the withdrawing of all acts:
&amp; if per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture ſhe leaueth, or doth the like acts of vertue as
before, then ſhe leaueth and doth them, not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to her proper will,
but for ſo much as ſhe ſeeth the will of God to be, that ſhe leaue, or
doe them. Our Lord and maiſter him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe made this ſubtraction &amp;
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunciation in the garden, when he ſayd, <hi>non mea, ſed tua volunta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fiat:</hi> O Father, not my will be
done, but thine: to wit, my will would, as conformable to thine, Eternall
Father, ſuffer croſſe, and torments
<gap reason="missing" resp="#OXF" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:21191:53"/>his
power: in the ſame manner he inforceth himſelfe, and ſeeketh as much as
he can to deceaue vs, as often as he repreſenteth and put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth before vs, any
proper intereſt or commodity of ours: and as our Lord caſt him off, and
vanquiſhed him, in refuſing all things, &amp; not admitting any thing, ſo
ought we to ouercome him, and driue him away by the meanes of a perfect
anihilation of will, and to pray vnto our Lord, by this his holy &amp; entiere
renunciation he will giue vs his g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ace to obtaine full and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire victory ouer the diuell &amp;
ſin.</p>
            <div n="1" type="point">
               <head>The firſt point.</head>
               <p>MAN, &amp; whatſoeuer is created concerning their firſt
ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen, proceedeth of nothing; &amp; of himſelfe, by a thouſand wayes, to
wit, by infinite myſeries of ſoule <pb n="115" facs="tcp:21191:53"/>and body (to the
which he is ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect) is ready, and tending to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to the ſame
nothing, if God by his bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ty did not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſerue him; and a man ſinning is
made worſe then nothing. By the meanes of this conſideration of this our
firſt origen, and of all thinges created, we muſt endeauour or eſteem our
ſelues, and all thinges created as nothing, and not to loue, deſire,
ſeeke, or will any thing for our ſelues: and thus we ſhall get a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
anihilation of our will.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="point">
               <head>The ſecond point.</head>
               <p>VVE muſt conſider, that this true anihilatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the
ſoule to become a true portraict and reſemblance of the ſoueraygne
greatnes of God, for that it taketh away the hindrances that are betweene God
and the <pb n="116" facs="tcp:21191:54"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oule;
which is done by not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, or deſiring any thing: and thus ſhe becometh
a moſt faire, &amp; cleare mirrour or looking glaſſe. For euen as when we
would, that a glaſſe ſhould receyue in it ſelfe perfectly and entierely
the image &amp; figure of ſome obiect, it is need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, that ſo much the
further the one be ſet from the other, as the obiect is greater in it
ſelfe; ſo the greatnes of God being infinite, by the meanes of this
anihilation, the ſoule only taketh from it ſelfe all obſtacles that do
hinder it from vniting it ſelfe with God; but which is more, by a great
ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in her baſenes, &amp; a true know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the infinite
greatnes of God, ſhe draweth herſelfe infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly far from the ſame, and
by this meanes commeth to be diſpoſed, and able to receyue in her this
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finit obiect of God; and the ſame. <pb n="117" facs="tcp:21191:54"/>Lord by the
pleaſure he taketh, &amp; infinit loue that he beareth to this ſoule,
imprinteth and engraueth preſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tly in her, a true reſembla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce image, &amp; portraict of all his
great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, euen to the laſt Center of the ſame.</p>
               <p>This anihilation is of great force to purge the ſoule of
paſſions, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king away entierely al the obiects of them, ſeeing that he
that hath no will to any thing for himſelfe, hath not what to deſire, loue,
feare, or hate: whereof commeth alſo that it purifyeth the ſoule,
concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the intention, taking away all pretence of any created end
whatſoeuer in all our actions, &amp; maketh it truly capable to haue no will
to any other thing then to the pure glory of God in himſelfe, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhe
careth for nothing els; fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence alſo proceedeth an entire and totall
victory ouer all temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations; <pb n="118" facs="tcp:21191:55"/>ſeeing that vnto him that
deſireth nothing, the diuell hath not any obiect to preſent: and if he
doth, he is preſently reiected, and driuen away with this reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of
not deſiring any thing, &amp; by this meanes he is in all thinges
vanquiſhed and put to flight. The affects and principall ſignes of this
anihilation are theſe that follow.</p>
               <p>The firſt is, that the gifts &amp; gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that our Lord
communicateth to the ſoule that is endued there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, ſhe receiueth them
not, nor retayneth them in herſelfe, for ſo much as that which is nothing
ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not receyue in it ſelfe any thing, but receaueth them in God, &amp;
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferreth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto him from whome they proceed.</p>
               <p>Secondly, that ſhe doth not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriate the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to herſelfe, nor
reioi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce in ſuch graces in herſelfe, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is ſhe troubled if they be
taken <pb n="119" facs="tcp:21191:55"/>from her, or that ſhe happen to looſe them; but
equally, whether ſhe hauing them or no, ſhe remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth content in her
nothing.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, ſhe maketh no accompt of this grace, but for ſo much
as our Lord wilbe ſerued by the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the ſame.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, ſhe doth not eſteeme the grace in it ſelfe, but
for that by the meanes of it, ſhe commeth to a greater knowledge of the
giuer, and eſteemeth him the more.</p>
               <p>Fiftly, ſhe doth not exalt her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe for any gift or grace
that ſhe can receaue, but alwayes keeping herſelfe in her nothing,
remaineth in the ſame conceipt, and opinion of her baſenes.</p>
               <p>Sixtly, in the workes that ſhe doth, ſhe knoweth truly that of
herſelfe ſhe doth nothing, but diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couereth in a high manner the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine
aſſiſtance in them, and that it <pb n="120" facs="tcp:21191:56"/>is he which worketh
all, &amp; what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer happeneth vnto her, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though neuer ſo grieuous
&amp; hard to ſupport, yet with an entire pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce ſhe repoſeth in him.</p>
               <p>Seauenthly, in the tyme of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction, and dryneſſe of
ſpirit, ſhe is not mooued with it, neither ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth any remedy, or
conſolation, but with all ſubmiſſion imbraceth it, and giueth
herſelfe in prey vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it, as vnto a proper obiect of nothing.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="exercise">
               <head>THE EXERCISE of Diſappropriation.</head>
               <div type="introduction">
                  <head>The Prayer preparatory accuſtomed.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>IRST we muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider how truly was verified in our Lord
IESVS Chriſt, that which he ſaid of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: <pb n="121" facs="tcp:21191:56"/>
                     <hi>Vulpes foueas habent, &amp; volu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cres cali nidos, filius autem
hominis no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> habet vbi caput ſuum
reclinet;</hi> that is to ſay: the foxes haue holes, and the birdes of the
ayre their neſts, but the ſonne of the virgin hath not where to repoſe
his head; and how much are we obliged to ſeeke with al our power, to imitate
him in diſappropriating our ſelues of all things, for to anſwere the
infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite loue he beareth vnto vs, Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, we muſt pray vnto our Lord with
great feruour that he would impart vnto vs this grace: and we muſt make a
firme &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant reſolution to be willing to accept it, with all our
hart &amp; affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, &amp; to diſpoſe our ſelues per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly, &amp;
wholy to the exerciſe, and execution of all that it requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth of vs.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="1" type="point">
                  <pb n="122" facs="tcp:21191:57"/>
                  <head>The firſt point.</head>
                  <p>VVE muſt conſider, that this diſappropriation is a
reſolute will, that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth from God, to be willing to be entierly depriued,
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning our affection, and, as much as poſſibly is conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient, in
effect alſo of all that we haue, and this becauſe there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth therby
greater glory vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God. And by this is vnderſtood that we muſt depriue
&amp; diſappro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priate our ſelues, not o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly of al crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted things, in as
much as they nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, &amp; intertayne in vs ſelfe-loue, and all other
faultes, and imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tections that may be found in vs: but which is more, we
muſt alſo depriue our ſelues of that which toucheth vs nearer, euen of
ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, and graces that we receaue of God, of all ſatisfactio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tentment, <pb n="123" facs="tcp:21191:57"/>conſolation, &amp; of any other good, that
by the meanes of them we may attribute to our ſelues, reſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning all this
truly vnto God, not deſiring in them, nor in any liuing thing, other taſt
and contentme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, then that his holy will be entierly and fully accompliſhed
in vs and all perſons. And in the end being depriued of all proper intereſt
and the vertues, and celeſtiall graces remayning in vs, euen in their purity
and perfection, we then ought to acknowledge out ſelues moſt vnworthy of
them: &amp; the more perfect they be, ſo much the more do they belong vnto
out Lord. And therefore with an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire, and perfect reſignation we ought
moſt freely to offer them vnto him in this their naturall pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,
ſimplicity and perfection, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting them vnto their firſt ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen. And
moreouer we muſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <pb n="124" facs="tcp:21191:58"/>alwayes prepared to depriue our ſelues of all giftes,
graces, &amp; ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, as if it were to giue, &amp; make a preſent of them,
vnto any crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture whoſoeuer, as it ſhall pleaſe our Lord to ordayne, and
this for his loue, and for his greater glory and honour.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="point">
                  <head>The ſecond point.</head>
                  <p>THIS perfect diſappropriatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or renunciation, is a
depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, and participation of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine, which is infinitely proper to
God, if we may ſo ſay: and neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe concerning the affection, our
Lord depriueth himſelfe, with a meruaylous great and excellent perfection, of
al that he hath, with peace, tranquillity, repoſe of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and infinit
magnanimity. This we ſee in God the Father, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally communicateth
himſelf to the <pb n="125" facs="tcp:21191:58"/>Sonne, and Holy Ghoſt: &amp; which is
more in effect, he communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth his gifts vnto vs in creation, conſeruation
of his graces, as he doth impart them to all his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, &amp; in
permitting ſinnes. And in the worke of the Incarnation, and in all other
myſteries of our redemption, we ſee how he deba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth himſelfe in
thinges moſt baſe, diſappropriating, and depriuing himſelfe of the
contrary perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. And then when ſo many An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gells departed from him, and
ſo many ſoules yet doe the ſame, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing eternal damnation, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priueth himſelfe of them, and of
ſo many graces which he hath im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted to them: we ſee in him the ſame
diſappropriation alſo in infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite other manners which cannot be
explicated. Of this may be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered, that this is a moſt high per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to
imitate God himſelfe in <pb n="126" facs="tcp:21191:59"/>foreſaid manner, by the means
of ſuch a diſappropriation.</p>
                  <p>The principall effects that this diſapropriation worketh, and
pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth in the ſoule, are theſe that follow.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, that the gifts that ſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyueth of God, ſhe
receaueth and vſeth them, as if ſhe had not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued them, not putting any
affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but offering the loue which ſhe might haue to them, &amp;
the gifts of God themſelues to him from whome they proceed.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, that ſhe reioyceth in the gifts that ſhe ſeeth
in another, although ſhe hath them not her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, as if they were her
owne.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, it maketh her rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and prompt to depriue herſelfe
of the graces and giftes which ſhe hath reccaued, to enrich her neighbour
therewith, and ſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyceth much in this.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="127" facs="tcp:21191:59"/>Fourthly, when ſhe findeth herſelfe
depriued of all giftes, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well ſpirituall as corporall, and of all graces
in what manner foe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, ſhe remayneth alſo content, as if ſhe had not
receaued them, and is not troubled, nor diſquiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted any thing at all. She
know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth well all her neceſſities, and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeryes, but neuertheles ſhe
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenteth herſelfe in them, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing truly that ſhe hath nothing of
herſelfe, and that nothing apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth vnto her, being vnworthy of any
thing.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="exercise">
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:21191:60"/>
               <head>THE EXERCISE of Indifferency.</head>
               <div type="introduction">
                  <head>The Prayer preparatory, as accustomed.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>IRST, we muſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foundly thinke of the ſenſe of theſe
words, <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere ad dexteram meam &amp; ſinistram, non eſt meum dare
vobis, ſed quibus paratum eſt à Patre meo:</hi> that is to ſay: To
ſit at my right hand, and left, is not myne to giue you, but to whome it is
prepared of my Father. And how much more in reaſon are we obliged to be in
all thinges ſubiect, and to remit our ſelues wholy to the good pleaſure
of God by the meanes of a perfect &amp; totall indifferency?</p>
                  <p>We muſt demaund humbly this <pb n="129" facs="tcp:21191:60"/>grace of our
Lord, with firme re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, willingly to accept of it, and to put in
execution the diuine inſpirations by which we may be conducted &amp; guided
to the ſame.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="1" type="point">
                  <head>The firſt Point.</head>
                  <p>FIRST, Conſider that this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differency is a moſt excellent,
diuine, and high perfection, for that, although our Lord be of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and of
will moſt reſolute to all that he will doe, and to all that which he doth,
neuertheleſſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning his affection, he is wholy prepared to doe, or
not to doe any worke whatſoeuer, if it were ſo conuenient for him, and if
he had, or might haue any ſuperiour of whome he depended; and more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer
concerning the effect, we ſee that he doth put in execution this diuine
indifferency, in communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating <gap reason="missing" resp="#OXF" extent="2 pages">
                        <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="132" facs="tcp:21191:61"/>Secondly, this indifferency cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth one
to haue a great &amp; magna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimous courage, &amp; by it we are diſpoſed,
and made prompt, and prepared to all thinges: and of this ſpringeth a
ſincerity of hart, that maketh the loue of God to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe in the
ſoule.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, the ſoule that is indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent, accepteth, and with
all her forces conſenteth to, all that God will worke in her, and with great
promptnes putteth it in executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, although it ſeeme vnto her troubleſome,
ſharp, grieuous, and vneaſy to ſupport, repugnant to her inclination, and
her proper iudgement, or of what ſort ſoeuer it be: in which oftentymes
many ſoules doe fayle euen of ſpirituall perſons, who for want of this
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differency, and deceaued by ſelfe loue, doe hinder oftentimes that which
God would work in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="133" facs="tcp:21191:61"/>Fourthly, it maketh the ſoule prepared to
liue or dye, to receau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
conſolation or affliction, and to take all thinges in good part, that can
happen eyther to herſelfe, or others, and all the vniuerſall mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeryes
which our Lord permitteth to happen in his Church. Briefly ſhe receaueth all
thinges equally, &amp; in one manner, from the hand of God.</p>
                  <p>Fiftly, what thing ſoeuer ſhe hath ſhe ſetteth not her
affection thereon, how good, or ſpirituall ſoeuer it be, in which many
ſoules willingly ſtumble, propoſing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to themſelues in their actions,
a good intention truly in it ſelfe, but according to their faſhion, and
make great accompt of certayne exerciſes that they doe, and which they much
eſteeme. But the ſoule indifferent, ſetting all things aſide<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, conſidereth, and ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <pb n="134" facs="tcp:21191:62"/>with great
diligence, how to follow, and put in execution the pure, and true interiour
motions of grace, and diuine inſpirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and to doe whatſoeuer ſhe
knoweth may redound to the greateſt honour &amp; glory of God.</p>
                  <p>Sixtly, in tyme of conſolation, ſhe doth not purpoſe to
doe diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult matters, and of great perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, neyther doth ſhe ſuffer
herſelfe to be tranſported by the exceſſiue guſt, and ſweetnes that
ſhe feeleth therein; but all that ſhe purpoſeth to doe, is done with
repoſe, &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turity, alwayes conditionally, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the will of
God, to the end, that afterwardes in the tyme of deſolation, ſhe remayne
firme. ſtable, and conſtant in the ſame good purpoſes.</p>
                  <p>Seauenthly, in great Solemni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and like occaſions ſhe
doth not conſider, nor rely vpon her <pb n="135" facs="tcp:21191:62"/>owne induſtry,
neither doth ſhe make too long preparations: but vſing therein conuenient
diligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, dependeth wholy, and with great ſimplicity on God, ſuffering
herſelfe to be gouerned by him, as he beſt pleaſeth.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="exercise">
               <head>THE FOVRTH EXERCISE Of Conformity.</head>
               <div type="introduction">
                  <head>The Prayer preparatory in the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner accuſtomed.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>IRST we muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider in theſe worde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> (<hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> volum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tem Patri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> that is to ſay,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y meat is to doe the will of my
father which is in hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>en:)
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> in other like ſpeaches, the
gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> conformity that our Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>io<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <pb n="136" facs="tcp:21191:63"/>had with the will of his eternall father, ſo that in all
his workes he proteſted, that he pretended no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing, but entirely to
put the faine in execution. And of this we may gather how much more we are
obliged to do the ſame in his imitation, inforcing our ſelues as much, as
ſhalbe poſſible, and with the greateſt affection, to bend &amp;
ſubmit our wil to be conformable vnto Gods, and to conceaue an earneſt and
vehement deſire ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, which ought to moue vs hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to beſeech his
diuine maieſty, that by the vertue of the merits of his deare Sonne, our Lord
Ieſus Chriſt, and by the ſame confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity aforeſaid that was in him, he
would vouchſafe to impart vs aboundantly his grace.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="1" type="point">
                  <pb n="137" facs="tcp:21191:63"/>
                  <head>The firſt point.</head>
                  <p>VVE muſt conſider, that this Conformity is no other thing
then a totall and reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute dependance, &amp; ſubiection of our will, to
the diuine, in al our works, occurre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, chances, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer they be: and
moreouer that all things whatſoeuer they be, are neither good nor holy, but
in as much as they are beautified &amp; ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified with the will of God; and
although they be indifferent, yea &amp; ſeeme ſomtimes impertinent &amp;
not to the purpoſe, in ſo much notwithſtanding as they proceed and depend
of the will of God, they are very good, and tend to a very good end, and to the
glory of God; and therfore we ought to weigh wel, &amp; attentiuely to
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, how high &amp; perfect a thing <pb n="138" facs="tcp:21191:64"/>it is to be
thus co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>formed to what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer we find to be Gods will, in all things &amp; at
all tymes; and how much the endeauouring, &amp; pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſing of it importeth,
and how neceſſary it is, if we deſire to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne to great
perfection.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="point">
                  <head>The ſecond point.</head>
                  <p>CONSIDER, that this is a moſt high perfection of God
him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and which we ſee to ſhine in the diuine attributes; which in
their workes, and in themſelues are infinitly conformable to the will of God:
&amp; from hence ſprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth this vnſpeakable harmony in them, as is ſeene
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>uailouſly alſo in the diuine
diuine perſons, in all exteriour and interiour actions, aſwell in that
concerning created things, as in all increated acts of knowledge, loue,
enioying, ioy and infinit others. This confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity <pb n="139" facs="tcp:21191:64"/>is
ſeene alſo amongſt the bleſſed ſpirits &amp; ſoules in heauen,
who at the leaſt ſigne they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue of the will of God, are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes
prepared to obey, and do obey it with great pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ptnes: it is alſo ſeene in all created thinges, and euen in
inſenſible creatures, as is read in the Goſpel, <hi>qui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> &amp; venti ebediunt
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> for that the ſea, and
the windes obey him; but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue al things it is moſt apparent in the ſacred
Humanity of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt with the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d Perſon of the Trinity
(to whom it it vnited) and with his eternall Father, and in the inferiour part
with the ſuper<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>our in all his
pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, affections, and operations: &amp; likewiſe it is ſeene truly and
per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly in the naturall repug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ance that he felt, in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideration of the torments, pains, and
exceſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>e
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours that he was to ſuffer:
and <pb n="140" facs="tcp:21191:65"/>how much the more he did really &amp; ſharply feele
them, ſo much the more he conformed himſelfe with an vnſpeakable repoſe
to the will of his Father, in deſiring them; ſo much the more increaſed
in him the repugnance, and ſenſibility of the griefes, in ſuch ſort,
that the contentment in this conformity, did not bring him any aſſwage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
of his ſorrowes, but only made that his will ſweetly repo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in them,
and with ſo prompt and ready mind, he willed and deſired the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that if the
Iewes had not crucified him, he himſelfe (if ſuch had bene the will of his
Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) was prepared to haue done it. We ſee alſo the like conformity in
his moſt holy mother; which, next vnto this of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, was
aboue all things crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted moſt ſingular &amp; moſt perfect. And we muſt
conſider that all the <pb n="141" facs="tcp:21191:65"/>foreſaid conformities are
repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the diuine Eſſence, which conteyneth in it ſelfe all
things, &amp; ſhineth infinitly in them, and in a manner that ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be
explicated, from which proceedeth great ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and glory vnto God.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="effects">
                  <head>THE EFFECTS OF this Conformity in a ſoule endued therwith,
are theſe that follow.</head>
                  <p>FIRST it cauſeth that the ſaid ſoule ſtudieth, &amp;
laboureth with great affection, and diligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce to vnderſtand and know in all
thinges what is the will of God, &amp; to put it promptly and readily in
execution, and not to care for any other thing.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. She findeth in all thinges repoſe, &amp; tranquillity
for the aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance ſhe hath, that in all thinges the will of God is
accompliſhed.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb n="142" facs="tcp:21191:66"/>3. She enioyeth great liberty of
ſpirit, free from all ſcruples, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quietnes, and inward bitternes, ſaying
often vnto our Lord, Thou knoweſt Lord, that I deſire no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing but
the accompliſhing of thy holy will, make me to know it, I beſeech thee.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. She accepteth, and recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth afflictions, &amp;
tribulations as preſents ſent immediatly from the hand of God, attributing
them to no other cauſe.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. She is not troubled for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, neither doth ſhe
lament, nor co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine vnto God, but to the imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our Lord Ieſus
Chriſt, ſaith, <hi>Non mea, ſed tua roluntas fiat;</hi> not myne but thy
will be done.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. She taketh pleaſure, &amp; reioi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth in them: and
the greater they are, and more contrary vnto her, ſhe maketh her commodity
the more by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, by a greater know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg <pb n="143" facs="tcp:21191:66"/>of God, and a
perfect ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion vnto his diuine will.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. When ſhe is calumniated, &amp; perſecuted without
any fault of her owne part, or any occaſion giuen, ſhe doth not ſeeke to
iuſtify and excuſe herſelfe, but leaueth all entierly in the hands of
God, for to ordayne the whole as he ſhall pleaſe.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. Yf by wearyne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour ſhe feele ſome vnquietnes, yet ſhe finds
repoſe, conſidering that this is the will of God, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming herſelfe
vnto the ſame, without ſeeking in this any parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culer intereſt, or good
vnto her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="exercise">
               <pb n="144" facs="tcp:21191:67"/>
               <head>THE FIFTH EXERCISE of Vniformity.</head>
               <div type="introduction">
                  <head>The Prayer preparatory is to be made as accustomed.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>IRST, to conſider in theſe words, <hi>Pater mi, non mea
ſed tua voluntas fiat:</hi> Father, not my will, but thy will be done, the
great vnion that the Son of God had with the will of God his Father in a matter
ſo difficult, contrary, and grieuous to nature, and ſo vnbeſeeming (as
may be thought) his greatnes, as his paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was; and of this we muſt
ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, by how much greater reaſon we are obliged to doe the like, in 
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:21191:67"/>the imitation of ſo rare an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of our Lord Ieſus
Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>Secondly we muſt with an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme deſire ſeeke to obtayne
this grace, and inſtantly to pray vnto the eternall Father, that he will make
vs worthy of it, by the m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of
his deare Sonne.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="1" type="point">
                  <head>The firſt point.</head>
                  <p>VVE muſt conſider that this vniformity, beſides that which
is contayned in the Conformity, doth more vnite the will, with that of Gods.
This ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth from vs all repugnance, and difficulty, for that in all things we
not only wil, what our Land wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth, but moreouer we are inci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed, and mooued to will it, only f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> the reaſon that God wil
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> and all our contentment i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfy the diuine will, fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <pb n="146" facs="tcp:21191:68"/>vnion
that we haue with it: and this for the loue of it ſelfe, and not for any
other reſpect. And the ſame loue inciteth vs to the ſame vnion with our
euen Chriſtian: according to that which is writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the Acts of the
Apoſtles: <hi>Erat credentium in Domino cor vnum, &amp; ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mavna,</hi> al
the faithfull of our Lord had one hart and one ſoule in the primitiue Church.
This vniformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſhineth, and is plainely ſeene, firſt in thinges wanting
life, the which by an inſtinct of nature in ſo great diuerſities of
operations agree altogeather to execute mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailouſly whatſoeuer they are
or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyned for by God; and altogea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther accompliſh vniformely this moſt
beautyfull, moſt excellent and meruaylous order, and har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of this world;
as we ſee for example in a houſe well ordered, that many ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts
performing du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <pb n="147" facs="tcp:21191:68"/>diuers offices that are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded them
by their mayſter, come finally to accompliſh, &amp; finiſh all, as one
only affayre. But this vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity ſhineth much more perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctly in heauen
amongſt the happy ſpirits, and ſoules, in whom by the efficacy of loue,
the diuine will cauſeth one hart, ſpirit, and will, as if truly all
togeather were but one, by a moſt ſingular vnio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the ſupreme will:
but aboue all it ſhineth moſt highly and meruay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly in the diuine
attributes, that agree, and accord in the eſſence, &amp; diuine will, in
the diuine perſons, &amp; in the actes that they produce.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="effects">
                  <head>THE EFFECTES of this Vniformity in a ſoul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, are theſe that f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </head>
                  <p>THE Firſt is, that the ſoule that is endued with this
vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity, <pb n="148" facs="tcp:21191:69"/>not only contente<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in al that which is Gods
wil, but moreouer vniteth herſelf with the ſame of God, and by this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
made one ſelfe thing with it, ſhe reioiceth equally in all things, only for
no other cauſe, but for that the diuine wil is pleaſed ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, &amp;
will haue it ſo.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. In all places, and in all thinges ſhe findeth God,
and vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth herſelfe with him, &amp; all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures ſerue her as a ladder
to rayſe her vnto God.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. For the that ſinnes ſhe fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth into, ſhe is
grieued for the offence that is againſt Almighty God: but euen of them alſo
ſhe taketh occaſion to abaſe herſelfe, and that with ſo much greater
ſubmiſſion, penetrating into the conſideration of the loue, with which
God hath permitted them, ſhe vniteth herſelfe vnto him.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <pb n="149" facs="tcp:21191:69"/>4. How much the more it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to
her ſometimes that ſhe is depriued of all grace, aba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>doned of God, and left
as ouerwhelmed in her miſeries; ſo much the more, by the meanes of them,
ſhe vniteth herſelfe with God, knowing well, that the graces that ſhe
firſt felt in aboundance, are retyred into God, and that they are kept, and
preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued more ſecurely in him, then when ſhe felt them in her ſelfe;
&amp; is contented, and more reioyceth to ſee them in God, then in
her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: and therefore rayſing and v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niting herſelfe with God, goeth to
find them in him, as in their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per origen, and conuenient place.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Being afflicted with any temptation eyther of the
diuell, or other creature whatſoeuer, ſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecteth, and reſiſteth all
the euill that might happen vnto her by it, and withall acknowledging ſuch 
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:21191:70"/>creatures to be miniſters of God, who permitteth them
for his grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter glory, euen by the meanes of theſe temptations ſhe commeth
to vnite herſelfe with God.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. How much the more ſhe feeleth herſelf fauoured of
God by imparting his celeſtiall graces, and how much the more excellent,
&amp; of greater conſequence they are, ſhe comming afterwardes to leaue
them for to vnite herſelfe more fully &amp; perfectly vnto God, from whome
theſe foreſayd graces pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed: ſo much the more ſhe ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that
ſhe made much leſſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme of the giftes then of the gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. In all her interiour and exteriour operations in a
moment &amp; twinkling of an eye, ſhe vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth herſelf with God, to know in
them his will, &amp; to put it preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in execution: and by this all her 
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:21191:70"/>actions are done without any diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate affection,
propriety, or particuler reſpect.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="exercise">
               <head>THE SIXT EXERCISE Of Deiformity.</head>
               <div type="introduction">
                  <head>The preparatory Prayer accuſtomed, before the
Exerciſe.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the beginning, &amp; in conſideration of theſe wordes of
our Lord, <hi>Ego dixi Di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
eſtis:</hi> I haue ſayd, you are Gods &amp;c. and in this that he ſayd
vnto his Father, <hi>vt vnumſint, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Pater in me, &amp;
ego in te, vt &amp; ipſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> in nobis
vnumſint,</hi> that all may be one, as thou my Father art in me, and I in
thee, ſo alſo that they may be one in vs. Heere we muſt end<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour <pb n="152" facs="tcp:21191:71"/>to
penetrate into the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency, &amp; greatnes of the perfection we are called
vnto by our Lord Ieſus, to wit, to vnite our ſelues in ſuch ſort by
efficacy of wil, and by the vehemency of a louing affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, to the diuine
wil, that being transformed into the ſame, we be no more, as we may ſay,
our ſelues, nor that which we were before, but like vnto God, &amp; in God
him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, Deified to the imitation of the vnion of the Sonne of God, with
his eternall Father.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Being proſtrate, with a moſt profound
ſubmiſſion in the depth of our nothing, in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the height
of his greatnes, as altogeather aſtoniſhed, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lying on the loue which
incited him ſo much to abaſe himſelfe, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vnto vs, thereby to rayſe
vs vp to himſelfe, we muſt craue of this loue a correſpondence of
affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, <pb n="153" facs="tcp:21191:71"/>which may liue in vs with a vehement deſire
of this true and perfect Deiformity in him.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="1" type="point">
                  <head>The firſt point.</head>
                  <p>VVE muſt conſider, that this Deiformity conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth to
haue our will vnited by ſuch efficacy of loue, with the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine, that ſhe
feele no more from henceforward herſelfe, as if verily ſhe were not at all,
but that only ſhe feele in her the diuine will, &amp; that all her actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s,
deſires, &amp; works tend to the only accompliſhing of the ſame. In
ſuch ſort, that euen in vertues, and holy thinges, ſhe wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth them no
more, with a created will, nor by it, but only by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>created, made hers by
an e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> transformation into it; conſidering that our Lord Ieſus
intended to ſhew this in theſe words, <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d
v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>luntas fia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <gap reason="missing" resp="#OXF" extent="2 pages">
                     <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="point">
                  <pb n="156" facs="tcp:21191:72"/>
                  <head>The fourth point.</head>
                  <p>THAT the humanity of our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, and of his
moſt holy mother, &amp; of all the bleſſed, by the working of God in
them, and by the knowledge, and enioying that they haue of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>inity, are as it were ſwallowed vp,
and rayſed into this foreſayd being, and vnity, and in the ſame moſt
perfectly deified: and finally that all the Saints, and the iuſt yet vpon the
earth, are tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>sformed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, &amp; from thence afterwards returne to their
being, as a drop of water being caſt into a great veſſel full of wyne, is
changed into the ſame, &amp; after being out of the ſayd veſſell,
returneth to his firſt being.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="point">
                  <pb n="157" facs="tcp:21191:72"/>
                  <head>The fifth point.</head>
                  <p>VVE muſt conſider, that after the ſoule is ariued vnto
ſuch an eſtate, that ſhe hath taken away, by the vertue of this Deifying
loue, and of the other aforeſayd lights, all that might hinder the working of
God in her, then hath ſhe attayned vnto this Deiformity; and this Deiformity
produceth theſe effects that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. She is Deiformed in all her actions, doing them, as if
God did them, and not herſelfe; &amp; th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> in them, &amp; by them entreth wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vnto God, and acknowledgeth him, &amp; enioyeth him.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Euen a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> a
ſinner doth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> action but out
of God, being <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ed of his grace, euen ſoon the
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſuch afoule doth not find 
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:21191:73"/>or doe any thing in which God is not, and by meanes
whereof, ſhe doth not enter, and vnite herſelfe vnto God.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. She eſteemeth not of any thing, but in as much as it
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth from God, or that it be done for God, &amp; in God.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Although that ſomtymes our Lord hide, and withdraw
him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe from ſuch a ſoule, yet in this ſubtraction, &amp; hiding,
ſhe retireth wholy into God, hiding herſelfe in him, without any ſweetnes
or feeling: yea how much the more, that by meanes of this rigour, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing,
ſharpnes, and bitternes, it ſeemeth that ſhe is far from God: ſo much
the more ſhe returneth, is Deiformed, and repoſeth in him.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Being moſt certains and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured, that ſhe
herſelfe, as of her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, cannot performe any thing that is good, by
reaſon of her to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall <pb n="159" facs="tcp:21191:73"/>vnability, knowing truly that
ſhe is nothing, hath nothing, and can doe nothing of herſelfe; ſhe is not
confounded, nor any whir troubled, yea euen in the middeſt of confuſions,
ſhe findeth herſelfe much aſſured, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tented, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing certainly
that ſhe ſeeketh not any thing proper, &amp; that nothing of hers is
therin, but God doth all imediatly.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Although ſhe ſhould raiſe the dead, and do ſuch
meruailous workes, &amp; great things, yet ſhe would neither care, nor
eſteeme of ſuch workes, or be moued with them; but in as much as God would,
ſhe ſhould: &amp; although ſhe ſhould poſſeſſe al the
treaſures of heauen &amp; earth, ſhe would not eſteeme of them in
themſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>, nor for herſelfe,
but refer, and offer vp all thinges vnto their firſt ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen, from whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce
they p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ded.</p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <pb n="160" facs="tcp:21191:74"/>7. Although ſhe knew ſenſibly
that ſhe had God in her, yea and though it were in the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as our
bleſſed Lady his holy Mother had, ſhe would not be moued any more, then
if ſhe did not perceaue any ſuch thing at all or that ſhe had him not in
her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, but in God, only imitating heerin the glorious virgin Mary, who
hauing in her armes our bleſſed Lord, held him, as if ſhe had not had
him, but as if her ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes had ben Gods, &amp; as though he held himſelfe,
&amp; this was the moſt excellent Deiformity of this moſt pure ſoule.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. When the ſoule that is come to this Deiformity,
ſeeth herſelfe to be prayſed, ſhe taketh no maner of pleaſure therin,
neither is ſhe troubled, afflicted, altered, or mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued any whit at all, for
ſo much as ſhe is wholy in God, and recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing <pb n="161" facs="tcp:21191:74"/>the
praiſes that belongeth to God, referreth and offereth them all vnto him.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. Two ſoules Deiformed, hauing betweene them great
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity of affection, inter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ayning one another with mutuall loue of very great efficacy, &amp;
with great diſappropriation; and therfore being to be ſeparated one fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
the other neuer ſo farr, for the greater glory of God, do care nothing at
all, nor are they any thing diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieted, for whatſoeuer accident, how great
or grieuous, that may befall them.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. If God would publiſh to the world the Deiformity
that he hath giuen her, ſhe would not be diſquieted or troubled, but would
ſay, Lord thou haſt done it, doe whatſoeuer it pleaſeth thee, for the
whole work is thine.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <pb n="162" facs="tcp:21191:75"/>
            <head>OF SELFE-LOVE.</head>
            <div type="introduction">
               <p>THERE are three fortes of ſelfeloue; the firſt is in a
worl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dly perſon, who liues amidſt the honours, greatnes, and dignities of
this world.</p>
               <p>The ſecond is in a ſpirituall, perſon, who deſireth to
ſerue God, &amp; this maketh him to ſeeke ſwet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, conſolation and
light, hauing a deſire to ſerue God.</p>
               <p>The third is in perſons that haue made ſome progreſſe and
are aduaunced in the ſeruice of our Lord, which is ſuch that with the
ſame, they mingle a deſire to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit greatly, and to ſtriue for
perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
               <p>Therfore great watchfulnes &amp; heed is neceſſary, to be able
to know it: &amp; for this end, it is need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to examine very exactly thy 
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:21191:75"/>interiour, and to weigh well, whether ſuch a deſire be
with paine and anxiety, or not: and when it is found to be with af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction and
trouble, the perſon may be aſſured it is ſelfe-loue, and it is the more
ſubtile, in that there increaſeth with this payne, a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter deſire of
perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Now he that will profit indeed, muſt be wary to tak away the
hindrance, which is ſelfe loue, &amp; to hope alwaies in God, &amp; to haue a
firme confiden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, that vnto who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> almighty God giueth ſuch a deſire, he
will alſo giue ſtrength &amp; meanes to bring the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to perfection, when it
ſhall be expedient for his honour and glory.</p>
               <p>And we muſt not think that for any diligence the ſoule can
performe, ſhe can ariue therunto, but rather with a ſincere
ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion vnto God, and with an ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration <pb n="164" facs="tcp:21191:76"/>as it
were inſenſible, ſhe ſhall come to haue the accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of her
deſire. And ſo in this eſtate, ſhe muſt be as a little infant that
ſucketh, whoſe operations are of that quality, that they giue ioy and
conſolation to the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and this for the innocency &amp; purity which
is in them, which maketh ſuch creatures not only agreable to the Creator, but
alſo to thoſe that behould them; euen ſo a ſoule that would be depriued
of proper loue, ought in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to imitate ſuch actes, that is to
ſay, that euen as a litle infant deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth neither this, nor that, but
on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that which maintaineth his life to wit, milke, &amp; this without any
ſelfe reſpect: euen ſo a ſoule ought to do the like, that is to ſay,
to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire only that which giueth her life, which is God himſelfe: and with
how much the greater ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity, <pb n="165" facs="tcp:21191:76"/>fidelity, &amp;
conſtancy ſhe ſeeketh God, in the in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iour of
her ſoule; ſo much the more ſhe maketh herſelfe agreeable, &amp;
plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to his diuine Maieſty.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="conditions">
               <head>THE CONDITIONS that a ſoule ought to haue to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme that
which hath bene ſpecified, are theſe that follow.</head>
               <p n="1">1. THE firſt, is to deſire to be euen as perfect as God
would haue her, and when, &amp; in the manner he pleaſeth.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To take away all hinderan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that may any way impeach
the executio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſuch a deſire in her and endea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>our that there ſhould not be any
thing betweene God and her, no not God himſelfe, in regard of the pleaſure,
and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment that is accuſtomed to <pb n="166" facs="tcp:21191:77"/>ſpring of the
knowledg and fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling that ſhe hath of God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: for although that the
ſayd pleaſure, and contentment be not euill, nor any ſinne, yet
notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding it hindereth, ſo that the diſappropriatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doth not
ariue to his perfection. Therfore if ſomti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes the ſoule take contentment
or pleaſure in her ſelfe, &amp; remaine buſied in creatures, vnder the
ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow and pretence of the Creator; ſhe putteth God himſelfe as a
hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, between him &amp; her ſoule, &amp; diſuniteth him from the
ſame, for the reſpect ſhe hath of that which proceedeth from his
diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, or is appertaining vnto him.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Not to take care, or be to much grieued if ſhe attain
not to that height of perfection, vnto which ſhe findeth herſelfe called:
for God is infinitely pleaſed to
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> a ſoule in paine for his
diuine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <pb n="167" facs="tcp:21191:77"/>the Kingly prophet Dauid ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſaid ſo much in his Pſalme 90.
<hi>Cum ipſo ſum in tribulation<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>:</hi> that is to ſay, I am with him in tribulation. For the
interiour tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulations make a ſoule more ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable then the exterior, to
receaue particuler graces from God; yea ſometymes ſo great, as cannot be
thought or imagined: Therefore a ſoule ought to tak great heed, that ſhe
doe not grieue or torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, if ſhe attayne not to the top of the
perfection ſo much deſired; for that ſometymes God giueth great
perfection, and yet with the ſame a ſoule ſhall not be ſo agrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to
his diuine maieſty, as ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that hath it not, but doe on their part al
that poſſibly they can to haue it. For hauing the ſaid per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection ſhe
will haue a ſati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and
contentment in herſelfe, the which although it be good, it 
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:21191:78"/>will not be ſo pleaſing to our Lord, as the payne and
affliction that a ſoule ſuffereth for his loue: but with this payne and
trouble ſhe ought to be wholy conformed to his diuine will, without
diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet, and not to ſeparate herſelfe any thing at all from the loue of
God, for otherwiſe it wilbe ſelfe-loue.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="effects">
               <head>THE EFFECTS of Selfe-loue.</head>
               <p>THIS Selfe-loue, although it be called in this manner, ought
rather neuertheles to be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led want of loue to our ſelues, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, death,
a ſelfe-venome, or poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: for that it hath no regard, nor reſpect,
eyther to life or health, to body or ſoule, nor to any other thing: it
eſteemeth of nothing but what it affecteth, it regardeth not God himſelfe.
This ſelfe-loue was <pb n="169" facs="tcp:21191:78"/>firſt in Lucifer whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he made
grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter eſteeme of his owne excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, then to be with God in Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe,
wherby he incurred preſently death vnto himſelfe, to wit, to be ſeparated
from God: the like alſo happeneth to a ſoule, for it ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth her from
God, maketh her be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come inſenſible, taking from her the light of reaſon,
to be opinia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue, churliſh, and voyd of ciuility. Selfe-loue is like vnto
the heath called Dogs-tooth, which being not rooted out, commeth by little
&amp; little to haue ſuch force, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> marreth all other heathes, that are neere vnto it: euen ſo, if
this Selfe-loue be not taken away and
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out of our hart, it wil take
ſuck increaſe in our ſoule, that it will ſpoile and corrupt all vertues
and graces that are in the ſame; for
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> only it corrupteth the vertues
that we haue gotten by our induſtry; <pb n="170" facs="tcp:21191:79"/>but alſo thoſe
that we haue recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in Baptiſme, and in the other Sacraments. It doth
alſo the ſame in our ſoules, as the opilations or obſtructions doe in
our bodyes, which are the cauſes of infinite di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes. It maketh a man
proud and high minded, and afterwardes ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth him into the depth of
deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire. It giueth him a preſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſtrength, and hope to do what he
will, and afterwards makes him vnable, and cold in the ſeruice of God. It
cloatheth the ſoule, &amp; co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loureth it with diuers colours vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the
pretence of ſanctity, after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards deſpoyleth it and maketh it naked of the
meanes that might bring her to her Creatour. It is a venome by which the
ſoule beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth ſenſeleſſe, and is ruyned and deſtroyed. It is
like vnto the moſt hurtfull venome of the Aſpe: it gnaweth and conſumeth
without <pb n="171" facs="tcp:21191:79"/>being perceaued, and inchaunteth and betwitcheth
in ſuch ſort, that ſhe knoweth not what ſhe doth, nor what ſhe would;
but paſſing from one thing to another, ſhe tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menteth herſelfe, and
not being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to come to what ſhe deſireth, ſhe grieueth, fretteth, and
pyneth away; &amp; if any counſell her for her help, comfort, and profit,
ſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth as a ſenſeles body, not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending any thing, like to
one that had no life: finally the orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that the foreſayd ſelfe-loue
giueth vnto a ſoule, are theſe that follow.</p>
               <p>Firſt it maketh it vnlike vnto God and like to Lucifer: it
cauſeth it to be hurtfull vnto other &amp; diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing to herſelfe. It
maketh it a veſſell of contumely, or ſea of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity. A ſoule infected
therewith may be likned to a ſhip that is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to the waues, and
tempeſts <pb n="172" facs="tcp:21191:80"/>of the ſea, that is ſhaken with all
ſortes of windes; like vnto a ſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king water, a barraine ground that
produceth no kind of fruit that is pleaſant, an infected carren, and in a
word it is like an vnbridled &amp; vntamed horſe; but which is moſt of all,
ſuch a ſoule deceyueth thoſe that ſhe conuerſeth withall, for ſhe
ſheweth herſelfe as though ſhe were full of vertue &amp; holynes, &amp;
hideth inwardly the qualities of a venemous ſerpent.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="description">
               <head>A DESCRIPTION of Selfe-loue.</head>
               <p>SELFE-loue may be figured, &amp; repreſented, as a man without
eyes, and notwithſtanding hath foure, but none for God, but for himſelfe:
with two he ſeeth, and with other two forſeeth only that which is for his
commodity.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="173" facs="tcp:21191:80"/>He hath no eares to vnderſtand the voyce of
God that ſoundeth mediatly, or immediatly, to wit, he is not attentiue, when
he is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited inwardly to know his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faultes, and imperfections, but he hath
ſix earers to appropriate any thing to himſelfe: with two he heareth his
own praiſes, with two others he hatkeneth vnto that which may augme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t this
ſelfe loue, &amp; with the other two he is watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and attentiue, that
nothing be ſayd agaynſt him. He hath three harts, notwithſtanding he hath
not one that may bring him any profit for the good of his ſoule, or whereby
to come to perfection, for he hath not any affection, taſt, or feeling of
good. The firſt hart is for that which concerneth hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> exteriour, or interiour commodity in regard of his
body.</p>
               <p>The ſecond is for ſuch things at <pb n="174" facs="tcp:21191:81"/>he doth
negotiate with others, to the end the world may haue him in good
reputation.</p>
               <p>The third maketh him to ſhew a mild, and gracious countenance to
be beloued of all, hauing his lookes very humble, his wordes ſayre, and well
placed; outwardly an Angell, but inwardly a raue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning wolfe; in ſumme,
ſeeking no other thing then to pleaſe himſelf.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="description">
               <head>HOW SELFE-LOVE entreth, and intrudeth it ſelfe into all
things.</head>
               <p>THIS Selfe-loue is moſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile, and hideth it ſelfe,
entring and intruding into all things, euen into the Sacraments. Firſt
cauſing perſons to frequent them for the proper guſt they find
therein.</p>
               <p>Secondly to be well eſteemed <pb n="175" facs="tcp:21191:81"/>off by others,
&amp; alſo to couer ſome defectes: it thruſteth it ſelfe, &amp;
en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treth in the ſame manner, in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the word of God for the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
they take therein. It entreth into holy Orders, when the are receaued or vſed
for vanity, for ſome commodity, ambition, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther euill deſignement. It
thruſteth it ſelfe into marriages, when they mary for to ſatisfy their
concupiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, and appetites. It intrudeth it ſelfe alſo into the
practiſe of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, procuring that great paine &amp; trauell be imployed in
it, without hauing any good, right, or ſincere intention for the glory of
God, but rather for ſome other reſpect. It thruſteth it ſelfe, and
entreth into the exerciſe of Prayer, pretending to receaue therein taſt,
light, and feeling, vnder pretence to be vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto God; and in doing this,
the perso<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo infected, ſeeketh him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,
<gap reason="missing" resp="#OXF" extent="2 pages">
                     <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <pb n="178" facs="tcp:21191:82"/>vnto God.
It entreth alſo by a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne ſuperfluous, ouer great, and exceſſiue
deſire of the croſſe, but it is for the pleaſure that one taketh
oftentymes in the ſame croſſe, in which ſelf-loue much delighteth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="properties">
               <head>PROPERTIES of a ſoule infected with ſelfe-loue.</head>
               <p>SELFE-loue robbeth from God, what appertayneth vnto him, for it
ſtealeth and taketh from him his honour, by ſeeking to attribute the ſame
vnto himſelfe, as the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſy robbed our Lord of his honor, when he
ſayd, <hi>nou ſum ſicut coeteri b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum,</hi> I am not like vnto other men.</p>
               <p>Firſt this loue maketh the ſoule vnlike vnto God, being a
moſt ſimple obiect, an infinite purity; Self-loue maketh the ſoule
double, <pb n="179" facs="tcp:21191:82"/>crafty, and diſſembling, and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth it to
ſeeme other then it is.</p>
               <p>Secondly, it maketh her like vnto the diuell, for euen as the
di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell is neuer co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent, nor repoſeth; ſo the like miſeries doth
ſelfe-loue cauſe in the ſoule, for it cauſeth much vnquietnes, and many
trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles in her, not being able to find any repoſe or contentment. It
ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth her a lyar, and an enemy to truth, and by this meanes ſhe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth
hatefull vnto others; for that ſuch qualities are inſupporta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: moreouer
it cauſeth conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually fretting and vnquiet, for neuer finding any repoſe,
and not daring to deſire death by reaſon of this ſelfe loue, ſhe
tormenteth and afflicteth herſelfe without ceaſing. It bringeth her alſo
to beaveſſell of contumely, for that to ſatisfy herſelf ſhe doth euen
her beſt acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, deſiring prayers, the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, <pb n="180" facs="tcp:21191:83"/>and ſuch like thinges, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing for a foundation of all this her
ſelfe-loue. And thus the works become defiled, ſoule and infected with this
ſelfe-loue, and the ſoule by this meanes is a ſea of iniquity: for the
bottome of her imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons not being able to be found, ſhe is a ſea
without bottome, that is mooned and troubled with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary winds, &amp;
ſwolne with mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaylous great, fearefull, and hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible waues, being angry,
and euer oppoſing herſelf againſt thoſe that would affoard her any help
or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy. She is alſo like vnto a ſhip, expoſed to the tempeſts &amp;
raging of the ſea, for this ſoule ſayling in the ſea of ſelfe-loue,
euen as a ſhip in the ſea, ſo is ſhe combated on e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery ſide, making
ſhip wracke for a ſmal matter. She may alſo be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to a ſtinking
water, for ſhe runneth on euery ſide (as water <pb n="181" facs="tcp:21191:83"/>that
hath no ſtay) to ſeeke if ſhe ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> find contentment; but by reaſon of
her imperfections ſhe is very noyſome, and yeldeth an euill fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour vnto
thoſe that are pure, and cleane. She reſembleth alſo a bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rayne ground,
that produceth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but thornes, thiſtles, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuch vnſauoury
weeds, ſpoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling all the fruit of good workes. She is like vnto a ſtinking
carren, for this ſelf-loue infecteth the ſoule and maketh her ſerue him
as food to a rauen, and afterwardes to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a prey and repaſt to that
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fernal fiend whom ſhe reſembleth. Briefly this loue thus qualifyed, is
as an vntamed horſe without bit, or bridle; it will not be ruled by any
perſon, nor co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taine it ſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e,
neither by counſell, not by skilfull aduiſe, but it maketh the ſoule to
mayne as rooted in her proper ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, and ſelfe iudgement, whereby 
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:21191:84"/>ſhe becommeth incorrigible: and this happeneth
ſometimes to ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me ſpirituall perſon, vnder colour of ſanctity, which
is very hardly cured.</p>
               <p>This foreſayd Selfe-loue ſprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth of the delight that the
crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hopeth to enioy in thoſe thinges ſhe ſeeketh, and which do
appertay ne vnto her, and it grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to that paſſe, that ſhe eſteemeth
not of her life, nor of any other thing els: in reſpect of arrayning to what
ſhe ſo liketh. It procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth alſo of the nature wounded &amp; corrupted
in her iraſcible and concupiſcible powers, and euill habits, and cuſtomes
which haue gotten root in the ſoule. And this is vnderſtood, not only of
the firſt kind of ſelf-loue which is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon &amp; familiar to worldly
perſons, but alſo of the ſecond, wherwith of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes ſpirituall
perſons are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangled, <pb n="183" facs="tcp:21191:84"/>the which may be called
ſelf-loue, for the taſt, &amp; pleaſure that they ſeeke in ſpirituall
thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. It is vnderſtood alſo of the third kind of ſelf-loue in
ſpirituall perſons, who are already aduaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and profited in the way of
vertue, which may be compared to the poyſon of the diamond, that gnaweth a
creature, interiourly by litle, &amp; litle, but it leaueth no exteriour
ſigne, as other poyſons do: ſo this proper loue gnaweth oftentymes in
wardly the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, but it leaueth no mark or ſigne in the ſoule, but
killeth it, and bringeth it in the end to death, &amp; damnation. It is a very
euident ſigne of the forſaid ſelf-loue when our Lord hath giuen any
particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler grace to a ſoule, and when it pleaſeth him to depriue her of
it, ſhe falleth into great griefe and ſadnes.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="184" facs="tcp:21191:85"/>The root of this forſaid Selfe-loue lieth
hid vnder the colour of faygned holines, and guideth the ſoule by a very
ſtrait, and narrow way, and maketh it appeare, to thoſe that conuerſe
which ſuch a perſon, that the way to ſerue God is very ſtrait, and more
difficult, then in truth it is. It engendreth a great wearines of ſanctity,
aſwell in the parties that haue it, as in the perſons that conuerſe with
them; which is no true holines. It exci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth a great meruaile, and an
aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment with vnquietnes, which procureth to the parties a diſguſt
and confuſion, in ſeing that they cannot arriue to that perfection and
holines, which they ſee in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, wherby they remaine with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out repoſe,
which is a great ſigne that this holines proceedeth of ſelfe loue. And he
that wrote this diſcourſe witneſſeth to haue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued 
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:21191:85"/>&amp; found this many tymes in
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>iſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, to wit, that in thinking on the ſanctity of ſome
ſuch per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he much meruailed,
but notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding he did not fall into vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quietnes and confuſion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedies">
               <head>REMEDIES againſt Selfe-loue.</head>
               <p n="1">1. FIRST the ſoule infected herewith muſt ſeeke to
haue a perſon very much enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by God, that hath the diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of
ſpirits, with whom ſhe muſt confer of her troubles &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, and
according to his iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t eſteeme herſelfe to be ſick, and to haue need
of help, as in truth ſhe hath, and is not able to help her ſelfe.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Secondly ſhe muſt
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> mortify all her deſires
&amp; affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, aſwell, of
thoſe thinges that are <pb n="186" facs="tcp:21191:86"/>good &amp; holy, as of thoſe
that are indifferent, and not to run after them, eſpecially, when ſhe is
moſt prouoked vnto them, and for this effect it will ſerue her much to lay
open her hart to her ſpirituall fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſuffer herſelfe to be
gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and conducted by him.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Thirdly the remedy is to thinke that all thinges, how
good and holy ſoeuer they be, are not alwayes pleaſing to God, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
thoſe that come from him, and are required by him. And by this we may know,
that they come from him when the ſaid things do not moue vs, nor lift vs vp
vnto pride in hauing them, nor torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; afflict vs in hauing them not, but
bring with them a peace and tranquillity to the ſoule: in ſuch ſort, that
ſhe remayneth in as great repoſe in the execution of them, as if ſhe did
not execute them at all.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="187" facs="tcp:21191:86"/>4. The fourth remedy is to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider,
that to accompliſh ſuch de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires of this ſelf-loue, is to contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne
God, and to contradict, and be oppoſite to the diuine will, for ſo much as
Diuine loue, is altogea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther contrary to Selfe loue; and all our actions that
we are induced vnto by it, are contrary to the bleſſed will of God, and by
that meanes we become oppoſite, and contrary vnto him.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The fifth remedy belongeth to the ſpirituall father,
who to take away, and cleere the ſoule from all ſelfe-loue, in all that
ſhe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth in her actions, and deſires, muſt firſt ſeeke all the
meanes to penetrate into her hart, that is, to gaine her good opinion and
eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, and to be gratefull vnto her; &amp; afterwards he muſt begin
with great ſweetnes to apply his remedies, and ſo to cure and heale 
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:21191:87"/>her: which muſt not be done in ſuch open manner that
ſhe may perceaue it, but with ſome kind of diſſimulation, and as it
were in ieſt, making her to doe all thinges contrary to that ſhe herſelfe
diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth off, or deſireth to doe: As for example, if the ſaid
perſon be deſirous to goe vnto one place of recreation, to make her goe to
a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother: ſomtymes alſo not taking them away altogeather, but cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting
them, as if ſhe would mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tify herſelfe with long diſciplines, to make
her to vſe ſhort, for ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome it doth profit to withſtand proper Loue
altogeather at one blow, as to forbid her wholy diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciplines, except it be to
a perſon already aduaunced in the way of perfection, &amp; in the exerciſe
ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. And as this his dexterity ought to proceed of charity, &amp; loue:
ſo alſo ought ſhe to be ruled with the <pb n="189" facs="tcp:21191:87"/>ſame loue,
for ſo much as in ſuch cures and ſicknes, ſeuerity profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth nothing,
by reaſon that this ſelfe-loue is ſweet &amp; gracious, and maketh the
ſoule very tender and delicate: ſo that if ſhe be vſed with ſharpnes
&amp; roughnes, ſhe entreth preſently into diſdaine, flieth and abhorreth
the cure. And by this may be ſeene, that Selfe-loue is healed with loue, and
by loue.</p>
               <p>This ſweetnes is moſt neceſſary in ſuperiours, &amp;
principally when they treat with thoſe vnder their charge, of thinges
appertayning to the ſuperiour part, and ſpirit: for ordinarily in this
affaire all the euill proceedeth of this roote, and ſeuerity procureth anger,
and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine, and hindreth much: &amp; mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reouer the Phiſitian of
Selfe-loue muſt note, that he ought to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually diligent, &amp; not to
aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don the cure, but to doe as a Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian <pb n="190" facs="tcp:21191:88"/>doth, who
hath one grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſly ſicke in his charge, for he viſiteth often his
patient, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny tymes feeleth his pulſe, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer abandoneth nor leaueth
him, vntill he perceaue that he is in bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter eſtate, and that he beginneth
to amend.</p>
               <p>He muſt alſo note, that there be two ſortes of perſons
that are ſick of this ſelfe-loue: ſome of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are as it were in a
conſuming fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, the euill wherof hath already very much penetrated into
the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward part; and although oftenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes they are incurable, or at the
leaſt very hard to be cured, yet notwithſtanding, he muſt not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies
deſpaire of them, but muſt performe in their behalfe what the ſaid
corporall Phiſitian doth to thoſe that hath the forſaid diſeaſe, to
wit, to performe on his part, whatſoeuer he can, and to leaue 
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:21191:88"/>the reſt vnto God; but he muſt take great heed, that
he doe not beare himſelfe to harſh &amp; to auſtere, for that would be
very domageable, and pernicious.</p>
               <p>The others that are ſicke, are ſuch, and of ſuch an humor,
as they may be healed: and although it be needfull to vſe great ſwetnes,
&amp; dexterity in their behalfe, as hath been ſaid before, and that there is
great difficulty in the cure, yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding he muſt not deſpaire,
by reaſon of the difficulty that he perceaueth in the beginning; for the
cauſe of this difficulty is, that this proper loue, doth ſo much blind the
ſoule, that it doth not permit her to ſee clearly her faults, and
imperfections: and therfore ſhe not acknowledging herſelfe to be ſicke,
the euill can hardly be cured, ſo that one ought to imploy all his care, and
induſtry to make <pb n="192" facs="tcp:21191:89"/>her to enter into this knowledg, which
in the end wil ſerue very much for her remedy and cure.</p>
               <p>Firſt the ſaid ſpirituall father muſt take great heed that
he ſpeak not any thing of ſelf-loue, &amp; that muſt be ſhunned from
the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, leaſt the infirme ſhould be too much diſmayed, and fall
into too much feare: but he muſt a far off put before her, and cauſe her to
practiſe the exerciſe of diſappro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, depriuing her firſt of
ſome things not very difficult vnto her, afterwardes make her returne to
herſelfe, and cauſe her to know how ſhe was hindred in this loue,
although in chiding her, he ought to ſay nothing that may co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>triſtate her,
or to ſeeme to blame her, but rather by little and little make her know her
euill; notwithſtanding when ſhe knoweth it, or when ſhe is cured, then he
muſt mak her vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, <pb n="193" facs="tcp:21191:89"/>how great, and dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous it
was, for he muſt comport himſelfe in this behalfe, as a guid doth in a
iourney, who being to paſſe ſome dangerous ſtrait, ſayth nothing to
the paſſengers of the perill and daunger, but only en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courageth them to
follow him, &amp; afterwards hauing paſſed the ſtrait, hath no more care,
nor looketh backe vnto it; euen ſo, thoſe that treate with ſuch kind of
perſons, ought to be haue themſelues dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terouſly without making them to
thinke of the difficulty that they ſhall haue to mortify the ſaid
ſelſe-loue, ſometymes ſpeaking to them in parables &amp; ſimilitudes
in a third perſon, ſometymes by good coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, making them to
vnderſtand &amp; to come to the knowledge of their defects; then with
ſweetnes, and taking euer ſome good occaſion to make them to returne, and
enter <pb n="194" facs="tcp:21191:90"/>into themſelues.</p>
               <p>Whileſt I was writing a copy of this booke, our Lord inſpired
this vertuous Dame for whome it was firſt compoſed, that ſhe ſhould
ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertiſe me of this that followeth, that I might ſet it downe in the end
of this worke: to wit, that as there is an Angell appointed ouer proper loue to
rep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſſe it, and fight
againſt it; ſo there is another ouer the loue of God, to conſerue,
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, and augment it, who from the beginning of their creation were
deputed to this function, the one, &amp; the other not paſſing fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
then their charge. <hi>S. Gabrid</hi> was deputed ouer diuine loue, by the
meanes whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>of he was choſen to be
the meſſenger of the ſacred m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtery of the Inca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nation of the God, a work of moſt ſingular loue of Almighty God
towardes man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, vnto whome it was eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally <pb n="195" facs="tcp:21191:90"/>reuealed in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the moſt Bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>mity, when the diuine perſons
made their actes of reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>procall loue. <hi>S. Michael</hi> was alſo appointed
ouer proper loue; and therfore whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Lucifer rebelled in heauen againſt God,
ſeeking to be like to the moſt high, &amp; equalling himſelfe with him,
he was ordey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by our Lord to reſiſt him, as one that had a great zeale
of diuine loue, contray to this ſelfe-loue. Our Lord then reuealed this
ſecret to this holy Lady, and ſayd vnto her. Aduertiſe thy ſpiritual
Father, that he may learne, that when any one would heale a ſoule, infected
with Selfe-loue, he demaund my aydand ſuccour, by the prayers &amp;
interceſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of S. <hi>Michael</hi> the Archa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel: and when any ſoule
ſhalbe touched, &amp; ſurprized with diuine loue, it is needfull that ſhe
implore the fauour of S. <hi>Gabriel,</hi> to the end, <pb n="196" facs="tcp:21191:91"/>that by this meanes ſhe may more eaſily attaine vnto the
ſoueraigne perfection of the ſaid loue of God.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="appendix">
            <head>AN APPENDIX TO THIS ABRIDGMENT, whereby to aſcend to a moſt
high Perfection.</head>
            <div type="examen">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, preſuppoſed of all the eſtates before
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, euen vnto this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, coſiſteth in an vtter forſaking of
al prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces whatſoeuer, &amp; not to pretend any other thing, but God only,
in a moſt excellent, and a moſt perfect manner, in all our actions, whereby
we may attayne vnto a moſt high perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which conſiſteth in the
examen follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <pb n="197" facs="tcp:21191:91"/>diſtinguiſhed into ſeauen
points.</p>
               <div n="1" type="point">
                  <p>1. The firſt is, when the ſoule apprehendeth any trouble
or affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that of new is preſented vnto her. For that then by the
ſuggeſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the inferiour, or infirme part, the apprehenſion of ſuch
a croſſe is accuſtomed to be very vehement: and with this, a thouſand
exagge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations wilbe preſented, that will cauſe it to appeare more violent,
wherby the ſoule is accuſtomed to take this affliction with much
dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty, and many repugnances.</p>
                  <div type="remedies">
                     <p>To remedy this, and to prouide for it throughly, it is
neceſſary that the ſuperior part of the ſoule, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe all this
before her, as a iudge doth, who before he giue his ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, harkeneth to
the reaſons of both parties, prouided alwayes that ſhe be not mooued any
thing with their reaſons, but that ſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne <pb n="198" facs="tcp:21191:92"/>without paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or any kind of alteration, ſuſpending her
iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement, vntill ſhe find out what may be according to reaſon: and that
ſhe may the better vnderſtand it, theſe two meanes will ayd her. The one
is, that ſhe enter into her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and conſider how Almighty God knoweth,
and ſeeth all her troubles, and whatſoeuer ſhe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dureth, and therfore
ſhe ought to remit it wholy into his hands, to diſpoſe thereof as he
ſeeth moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient. The ſecond is to conſider, &amp; belieue
aſſuredly, that euen as the diuine bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ty deſireth nothing but our good;
euen ſo his diuine prouidence (which is hid from vs, not being permitted vnto
vs to ſeeke too curiouſly into it) know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth very well how to prouide &amp;
remedy all in time, and manner, as it ſhall ſeeme beſt vnto him, and not
as beſt liketh vs, nor as it may <pb n="199" facs="tcp:21191:92"/>beſt pleaſe vs. Of
this ſuſpenſion, and repoſe of ſpirit follow two things; the firſt,
that ſhe putteth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and reiecteth all the hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances, and trouble, and
the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceytes that might happen by this apprehenſion: and ſecondly it wil
follow, that ſhe ſhall come to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue a true, pure, ſincere, and
ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture apprehenſion of all her af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fayres.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="point">
                  <p>The ſecond point is, that when the ſoule is come to
receaue, and accept this affliction, as comming from God.</p>
                  <div type="remedies">
                     <head>REMEDIES.</head>
                     <p>SHE muſt not reſt herſelf heere, or permit herſelfe
to accept of it, as often many ſoules are accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed to doe, to wit,
baſely with an infinit number of difficultyes, of excuſes, and ſeeking of
them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, but ſhe muſt accept thereof
<gap reason="missing" resp="#OXF" extent="2 pages">
                           <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <pb n="202" facs="tcp:21191:93"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o offer it, &amp; returne
it vnto God, accepting it only in him, and for him.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="point">
                  <p>4. The fourth point, is to know, in what manner the
ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour part muſt ſuffer with the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour, and with the exteriour
ſenſes, in the repugnances, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarieties which they feele, as hath
bene ſaid before.</p>
                  <div type="remedies">
                     <head>REMEDIES.</head>
                     <p>THE ſuperiour part ought to doe all, that hath bene ſaid
before, in the behalfe of the inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, and weakeſt partes, in ſuch
ſort, that it be not with a certaine exceſſiue viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, which may
cauſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wholy to looſe their ſtrength, and vigour, or ſo as may
trouble, or make the ſoule puſillanimous and fearefull, or els vtterly
vnable to ſupport ſo great a blow; but ſhe ought for this cauſe
ſomthing to <pb n="203" facs="tcp:21191:93"/>ſuffer with them, and encourage them with
all the reaſons the can imagine, and ſhe muſt doe all this with the
greateſt diſcretion that ſhe can poſſibly, in giuing now and then
ſome relaxation vnto their trauailes, and afflictions, &amp; in ſeeking the
moſt conuenient remedies that ſhe can aduiſe her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe of. Euen as one
that would haue a horſe, or any other beaſt to ſerue his turne, will giue
him more meat, to the end he may be ſtrong, and able to trauaile better when
there is need. And when by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of diuine ſubtraction ſhe can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
vſe the force of any act of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſola<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>io<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſing vp of
her mind, ſhe ought to repoſe in this, and procure the partes that are
inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, to repoſe in the will of God, and this by meanes of the diuine
conformity, which will bring much more true and ſtrengthning 
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:21191:94"/>conſolation, although it doth not ſeeme ſo.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="point">
                  <p>5. The fift point is, how ſhe ought to comport herſelfe
with ſelfe-loue in this caſe, or the like.</p>
                  <div type="remedies">
                     <head>REMEDIES.</head>
                     <p>SELFE-Loue is accuſtomed to pretend &amp; ſeeke in all
thinges her owne intereſt, and particuler co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>moditie directly, or indirectly;
and it doth ſo alſo in this, vnder pretence of many good reaſons, yea
euen of vertues, and purpoſeth many thinges that are not to the purpoſe;
&amp; for this cauſe the ſoule with the purity of a right intentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ought
to diſcouer by the light of the loue of God, all his deceipts, &amp; oppoſe
herſelfe againſt this ſelfe loue very freely, and effectually; &amp; by
the force of a pure &amp; cleane loue, ſhe ought to reiect all parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culer
and ſelfe reſpect, and follow <pb n="205" facs="tcp:21191:94"/>purely that which God
ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire, and teach her.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="point">
                  <p>6. The ſixt point is, how that the ſuperiour part ought to
anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>were to the propoſitions or offers, that our Lord will make vnto her
concerning theſe paines, and affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, or other greater.</p>
                  <div type="remedies">
                     <head>REMEDIES.</head>
                     <p>AFTER this that hath byn a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue ſaid, our Lord is
accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed to make many propoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n to the ſoule: as for example, that
he will ſend her many other affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, or els make her endure this
preſent affliction along tyme, yea that we will cauſe her to ſuffer euen
the paines of hell; and then ought ſhe with great promptnes to be wholy
reſigned vnto God. He alſo is accuſtomed to giue the choice of two kindes
of afflictions for her to accept of one. And in <pb n="206" facs="tcp:21191:95"/>this
caſe rayſing &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ixing the
eyes of her ſoule wholy in the perfect loue of God, with a meruailous purity,
ſhe ought to make her ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in God, and this choice muſt be alwaies of
that which will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dound moſt to his honour and glory.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="point">
                  <p>7. The ſeauenth is, in what manner ſhe ought to behaue
her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, that ſhe may vſe all her pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in the execution of this
affaire, or of this affliction, and of all that which ſhalbe neceſſary,
to come to the height of this perfection.</p>
                  <div type="remedies">
                     <head>REMEDIES.</head>
                     <p>FOR as much as ordinarily in the exerciſing of all theſe
thinges, it is neceſſary that all the powers, &amp; faculties of the
ſoule concurre therunto, to put it duly in execution; ſhe ought fully to
reſolue with herſelfe to obſerue all <pb n="207" facs="tcp:21191:95"/>that ſhe hath
deliberated vpon, in ſuch ſort, that aſwell in generall, as in
particuler, ſhe may perfectly accompliſh, &amp; put in execu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>io<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all this that ſhe hath already
choſen, and reſolued to doe in the preſent affliction, or in any other
thing: and ſhe ought to take heed dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently to correct the faultes that may
happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the executio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>yther by
reaſon of her imagination, and repreſentation of afflictions, or of the
vnderſtanding, or of the will, or of all the other powers. And thus the
ſoule that is perfect, ſhall become much more perfect: and all this is a
diſpoſition vnto the ſtate, that re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dereth the ſoule who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diuine.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="religious_exercise">
               <pb n="208" facs="tcp:21191:96"/>
               <head>THE DAYLY EXAMEN of our Conſcience, eſpecially at Night.
§. 1.</head>
               <p>TO giue God thanks for al be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits formerly receaued, and
eſpecially of that preſent day.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To demaund grace &amp; true light, to know &amp; hate
our ſinnes.</p>
               <p n="3">3. To call our ſoules to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt, wherin we may haue
that day offended God: hauing ſpecial conſidera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>io<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſuch defects wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto we are
moſt inclined.</p>
               <p n="4">4. To craue pardon humbly of God for al ſins &amp;
defects, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of we find our ſelues guilty.</p>
               <p n="5">5. To make a firme purpoſe, through Gods grace to auoyd
ſin heereafter, with intention to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe thoſe wherein we haue
tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſed. Laſtly, ſay <hi>Pater noster. Aue Maria.
Credo.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="religious_exercise">
               <pb n="209" facs="tcp:21191:96"/>
               <head>THE PARTICVLAR EXAMEN to be made at three tymes, very
ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for the better diſpoſing, &amp; ſearching into our
ſelues. §. 2.</head>
               <p>THE firſt is in the morning when, aſſoone as we awake, we
muſt purpoſe to keep a dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>r watch that day ouer our ſelues, for the
auoyding of ſome ſinne or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfection, which we are deſirou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to amend.</p>
               <p>The 2. is at Noone, when we muſt demaund Gods grace, that we
may remember how often we haue fallen into that particuler ſin or defect,
&amp; be more heedful heer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after. Then, let vs make our firſt Examen, calling
our ſoule to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt, &amp; running ouer euery houre of the day to that
preſent, how often we haue fallen therin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to: &amp; let vs make ſo many
marke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <pb n="210" facs="tcp:21191:97"/>in the
former ſyne of the enſuing table. This done let vs purpoſe to keep our
ſelues more warily the reſt of the day.</p>
               <p>The 3. Time, ſhalbe at Night after ſupper, when we muſt
make the ſecond Examen, running ouer euery houre from the former exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination
vntill that, calling to mind, &amp; nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bring the times wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we haue
offended, making ſo many markes in the ſecond line of the table mentioned
before.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="additions">
               <head>FOVRE ADDITIONS very profitable, for the more eaſy &amp;
ſpeedy rooting out of any Vice, or ſinne. §. 3.</head>
               <p>THE 1. is, that as often as we commit that particuler ſinne,
we be ſory for it from our hart, in witnes wherof let vs lay our hand vpon
our breſt: which may be <pb n="211" facs="tcp:21191:97"/>done at all tymes, without being
perceaued by others.</p>
               <p>The 2. is, that at Night we number &amp; compare the mathes of
both lines togeather, the former line being appointed for the firſt examen,
&amp; the later for the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
&amp; let vs ſee, if from the former hath followed any amendment.</p>
               <p>The 3. is, that we compare the examinations of the firſt &amp;
ſecond day togeather, &amp; marke whether any amendment hath byn made.</p>
               <p>The 4. is, that by comparing two weeks togeather, it may
ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare what amendment hath byn made, or omitted.</p>
               <p>It is alſo to be noted, that the firſt of the lines
following, which is longer then the reſt, is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for the firſt day,
the ſecond ſomewhat ſhorter for the ſecond day, and ſo likewiſe for
euery day, ſhorter &amp; ſhorter. It being <pb n="212" facs="tcp:21191:98"/>meet that
the number of our faults be dayly diminiſhed.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>Sunday —</item>
                  <item>Mundy —</item>
                  <item>Tweſday —</item>
                  <item>Wedneſday —</item>
                  <item>Thurſday —</item>
                  <item>Friday —</item>
                  <item>Saturday —</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="advice">
               <head>CERTAYNE ADVERTISMENTS neceſsary for the better making of
our Prayer. §. 4.</head>
               <p>BEFORE Prayer, the Soule muſt exerciſe it ſelfe in ſome
acts of Humility, by conſidering its owne baſenes, and the greatnes of God,
with whom it is to treate, and falling down vpon our knees we muſt begin with
the ſigne of the Croſſe, bleſſing our ſelues, and crauing of the
diuine Maieſty grace, to ſpend that ſhort tyme <pb n="213" facs="tcp:21191:98"/>well,
which we are to imploy in that holy Exerciſe; ſo as all out thoughts,
words, and workes may be ſincerely addreſſed to the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter glory of
God. Moreouer we muſt imagine a certayne Compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of place, and therein
accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modate our ſelues in ſuch manner as is taught vs, by our ſpirituall
Father and Directour in that caſe. Finally we muſt perſwade out ſelues,
that we ſtand in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God, who is both within &amp; round about
vs, to the end that the imagination therof may incite vs to greater attention,
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fidence, and reuerence. Next we muſt aske of the diuine goodnes that,
which we deſire, anſwerable to the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter wherof the meditation is to be
made. For example, if I meditate of ſin, I will craue pardon for my owne
&amp;c.</p>
               <p>We muſt alſo make one, or more <pb n="214" facs="tcp:21191:99"/>Colloquies at the end, according to the motions, &amp; affection which
the ſoule ſhall feele in it ſelfe, in ſpeaking ſometimes to the
Bleſſed Trinity, ſometymes to euery one of the three Diuine Perſons, or
to the B. Virgin, or the Saints, giuing thankes other whiles for benefits
receiued, other whiles crauing Gods help, for getting of ſome one vertue in
particuler.</p>
               <p>The repetitions, that our B. Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther S.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gnatius teacheth in the firſt
Weeke of his Spirituall Exerciſes muſt be made after two, or three
meditations, in ſuch manner, as is ſpecified in the ſame place, making
three Colloquies, to wit, to the Father, to the Sonne, and to the B.
Virgin.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb n="215" facs="tcp:21191:99"/>
            <head>THE TABLE.</head>
            <list>
               <item>1. VVHAT Perfection ought to be preſuppoſed in the Soule,
that entreth into the practice of that which is treated of, in this
Diſcourſe.</item>
               <item>2. Two Principles wherein conſiſteth Perfection.</item>
               <item>3. Of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.
Eſtate: &amp; fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt of
Anihilatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</item>
               <item>4. Of the firſt Degree of Abnegation, Subtraction
Conformity: and of the Abiect on, &amp; Anihilation of himſelfe.</item>
               <item>5. The ſecond Degree.</item>
               <item>6. The third Degree.</item>
               <item>7. The fourth Degree.</item>
               <item>8. The fifth Degree.</item>
               <item>9. The ſix Degree.</item>
               <item>10. Of the ſecond Estate.</item>
               <item>11. Of the third, and laſt Eſtate.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <pb n="216" facs="tcp:21191:100" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>THE LADDER of Perfection.</head>
               <item>THE firſt Exerciſe of Anihilation.</item>
               <item>The 2. Exerciſe of Diſappropria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</item>
               <item>3. The Exerciſe of Indifferency.</item>
               <item>4. The Exerciſe of Conformity.</item>
               <item>5. The Exerciſe of Vniformity.</item>
               <item>6. The Exerciſe of Deiformity.</item>
               <item>7. Of Selfe loue.</item>
               <item>8. Of the Effects of ſelfe loue.</item>
               <item>9. A Deſcription of ſelfe-loue.</item>
               <item>10. Properties of a ſoule inſected with
ſelfe-loue.</item>
               <item>11. Remedies agaynſt ſelfe-loue.</item>
               <item>12. A ſupply of this Abridgment, to aſcend vnto a most
high Perfection.</item>
               <item>13. The Examen of our Conſcience.</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:21191:100"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
